<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth springing out of the earth that is, the truth of Christ proved out of the earthly promises of the Law : wherein is made manifest that the coming of the Messias cannot be for temporall things, according to the expectation of all the Jews : proved out of their own principles / by R. Solomon Franco ...</title>
            <author>Franco, Solomon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23205</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15347846</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204172</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501555</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2066A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15347846</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1188:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth springing out of the earth that is, the truth of Christ proved out of the earthly promises of the Law : wherein is made manifest that the coming of the Messias cannot be for temporall things, according to the expectation of all the Jews : proved out of their own principles / by R. Solomon Franco ...</title>
                  <author>Franco, Solomon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 71 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Flesher for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" and "The epistle dedicatory" signed: S.F.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur. Ex ædibus Lambeth. Julii 2. 1668. Sam Parker, reverendissimo in Christo Patri ac Domino, Domino Gilberto, divina providentia Archiepiscopo Cantuariensi, à sacris domesticus"--Opposite t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Messiahship.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Messiah --  Prophecies.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian converts from Judaism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex Aedibus <hi>Lambeth.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Julii</hi> 2. 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sam. Parker,</hi> Reverendissimo in <hi>Christo</hi> Patri ac Domino, Domino <hi>Gilberto,</hi> Divina Providentia Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiscopo <hi>Cantuariensi,</hi> à Sacris Domesticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Hebrew word diagram</figDesc>
               <q>Truth shall spring out of the Earth.</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth springing out of the Earth:</hi> THAT IS, The TRUTH of <hi>CHRIST</hi> Proved out of the EARTHLY PROMISES of the LAW. Wherein it is made manifest, that the Coming of the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> cannot be for Temporall things, according to the expectation of all the <hi>Jews.</hi> Proved out of their own Principles.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. SOLOMON FRANCO,</hi> A true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to our Lord and Saviour <hi>JESƲS CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Flesher,</hi> for the Authour, 1668.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:5"/>
            <head>TO THE Most Excellent and Mighty Prince, CHARLES II. By the Grace of God, KING of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SOVEREIGN LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an undoubted Truth, That the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures not onely teach us those Rules whereby we are to govern our selves as to God Almighty in matters of Religion, but also how we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our selves one towards another: therefore our Saviour <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> declared all the Law to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained onely in two Precepts, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to <hi>love God and our Neighbour;</hi> this word <hi>Neighbour</hi> comprehending in it all sorts of men, including in it that Justice and Charity which is proper from the Great ones to their Inferiours, as also that Honour and Respect which is due from all men to their Superiours, each one according to his degree and quality.</p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Jews</hi> do derive that respect due to Magistrates from the first Precept, that is, from God himself, by reason their Power and Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency over men proceeds from an express Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God to <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons after the Floud,
<pb facs="tcp:204172:6"/> (that is) to establish Judges and Governours: and there he doth grant and allow them so much of his own Power, that they may legally execute Justice upon all Offenders; for otherwise men could not have taken to themselves that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs only to God: but their Power being instituted and given from above, therefore Magistrates are intituled in the Scriptures <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Gods;</hi> and if so, it is but reason that they should be owned upon Earth as little Gods. Hence we may judge how much Love, Honour, Fear, Respect and Obedience is due to the <hi>Royal Person,</hi> as being the Head and Chief of all Magistrates, upon whose Pleasure all the rest depend, and thence do receive all their Power and Lustre. The <hi>Jews</hi> Laws as concerning Kings are so strict, that the least Misdemeanour committed against a King was punished with Death.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Talmudists,</hi> endeavouring to excuse King <hi>David</hi> concerning <hi>Ʋriah</hi>'s death, do note, that when <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> the Prophet comes to declare to <hi>David</hi> God's Displeasure as to that Fact, it is there said, <hi>And hast slain him with the sword of the children of Ammon:</hi> and hence they conclude <hi>David</hi>'s Sin not to be, that he slew <hi>Ʋriah,</hi> for he deserved it; but that he slew him with the Sword of the Children of <hi>Ammon.</hi> And their reason is express'd in those following words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ʋriah was a Rebell against the Crown, for he called</hi> Joab <hi>his Lord before the King:</hi> their meaning is, that <hi>Ʋriah</hi> was guilty of Rebellion, for before the King no man is to be called Lord but himself. <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, being well skilled in the Laws of that Kingdom,
<pb facs="tcp:204172:8"/> when <hi>Adonias, David</hi>'s eldest Son, would have crowned himself, the said <hi>Nathan</hi> coming then to King <hi>David</hi>'s bed-side, after <hi>Bathsheba</hi> had been there a while, to know his pleasure concerning that Affair, there saith, <hi>And Solomon thy servant,</hi> &amp;c. So that the Prophet would not call <hi>Solomon</hi> Lord before the old King, though he well knew his will that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> should succeed him. And though this their Interpretation may be taken of some to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious; yet howsoever here it is manifest their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Opinion was, That he that did commit such a Fault was to be punished with Death. For as in reference to God the least Imagination against his Divine Power and Majesty is a Sin unpardonable; so to <hi>Kings,</hi> that are immediate under God, and Gods upon the earth, the least Crime is reputed Treason. The <hi>Israelites</hi> were so zealous for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their Kings, that they own for a general Rule and established Law amongst them, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>A King that will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give his Honour, his Honour is not forgiven.</hi> Their meaning is, that though a King, out of his good nature, would have pardoned an Injury commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted against his Person, the Judges in this case ought not to take notice of his Mercy, but still punish the Delinquent, for fear of giving incouragement to others to presume to attempt any thing against Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majesty. So that all along they do derive the Honour of a King from that of God.</p>
            <p>The Lord enjoyned the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> to bring in every year the First-fruits of the Land he had given them, as an acknowledgment that all was
<pb facs="tcp:204172:9"/> his. Your <hi>MAJESTY</hi> being under God Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour and God upon the Earth, I do humbly conceive it my Duty to present to Your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Hands the First-fruits of my <hi>Christianity,</hi> to whom they properly belong, as <hi>Defender of the Faith.</hi> Moreover, there lies another Obligation upon me more then upon any other man, which indeed gives me the boldness to presume so high in this my humble Offer.</p>
            <p>The wonderfull Restauration of Your <hi>MAJE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY</hi> to these Your Kingdoms, (as I do manifest to the World in this my following Discourse) the Hand of the Lord appearing so eminently in it, was the first Motive that inclined me towards the <hi>Christian Religion:</hi> so that I receiving that Light and Influence from those Favours which the Lord hath pleased to bestow upon Your <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> how can I otherwise chuse but return them to the Fountain from whence they first sprang? From Your <hi>MAJESTY</hi> my Salvation first proceeded, and there I do humbly return the Reasons of my Conversion; hoping in Your Bounty and Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to reap that Acceptance which your <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY</hi> uses to bestow upon sincere spirits, which without Craft or double intention do declare their serious thoughts. So casting my self at Your Sacred Feet, I ever remain obliged to pray to the Lord for the Health, Life and Prosperity of Your Sacred <hi>MAJESTY,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The meanest of Your <hi>MAJESTY</hi>'s most faithfull Subjects, <hi>S. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:7"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, GEORGE L<seg rend="sup">d.</seg> B<seg rend="sup">p.</seg> of <hi>WINCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Jews</hi> Church-Government was so firmly settled, and their Laws so strictly observed, that no man was to take the liberty to himself to act any thing contrary to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Resolution of the <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> in any cause or matter whatsoever: it being so expresly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>17.</hi> Chap. of <hi>Deut.</hi> That when there should happen any Controversie amongst them, they were to goe up to the Priest or Judge that should be in those days, and to hearken and doe according as they were told there: and from their Sentence they were not to decline ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the right hand or the left. These words the <hi>Jews</hi> interpret thus; If they should tell you the <hi>right hand</hi> is the <hi>left,</hi> and that the <hi>left</hi> is the <hi>right,</hi> you are to obey them: for so it seems in the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>Levit.</hi> where it is said, That when all the Congregation should have committed a Sin through Ignorance, and that the thing should be hidden from the eyes of the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (Where it appears to be in a Case where, by the Consent of the <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> somewhat had been observed generally; the which afterwards by the same <hi>Sanhedrin,</hi> or by another that succeeded it, after more
<pb facs="tcp:204172:8"/> serious Consideration, was found to be unlawfull or unexpedient:) then they were to offer for the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of their Errour a Sacrifice. And the <hi>Jews,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their own Rule, expound here in this case the word <hi>Elders</hi> for those <hi>wise men</hi> which rule over them. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Who is an old man? He that possesseth Wisedom.</hi> And if one among them would presume to act or command others to doe contrary to the Opinion of the major part of the Assembly, although he should be in the right, and they in the wrong, yet nevertheless he was to be put to death; as it appears in the same Chap. of <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> above mentioned. There are several Examples in the <hi>Talmud</hi> concerning this matter; and it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly received amongst them, That if there should be an hundred Prophets on the one side, and an hundred and one wise men on the other; yet the Law shall be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Opinion of the major part: for, say they, The Law was given but once, and the Interpretation of it left to the Discretion of wise men in each generation.</p>
            <p>I will onely here set forth a Case which is told in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> the consequence thereof being in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension very notable, though for matter of fact each one has his liberty to believe as he pleaseth. The thing was this. There arose a Dispute and Controversie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one <hi>Rabban Gamaliel</hi> and <hi>Rabbi Josuah,</hi> whose Opinion being highly contradicted by the most part of the Assembly, he, the said <hi>Rabbi Josuah,</hi> considering the great reason he had on his side, and yet that he was so strongly opposed, expressed himself thus; If the Truth be on my side, let such and such things evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear: which they say happened accordingly; and
<pb facs="tcp:204172:6"/> yet for all this, they would not yield to his Opinion. And when he saw this, he more earnestly said, If the Truth be on my side, let a Voice come down from Heaven and declare it: and accordingly they say a Voice came down from Heaven, and said, <hi>The Law is according to the Opinion of</hi> Rabbi Josuah; <hi>but when there are many against one, the Law must be observ'd according to the Opinion of those many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were commanded to take on the First day of the Feast of Tabernacles the Fruit of goodly Trees, Branches of Palm-trees, and Boughs of thick Trees and Willows, and there to rejoyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord their God. Yet when this day happens to be on a Sabbath, they are forbidden by the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> to bring them, lest they should carry them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>four cubits</hi> length <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>in a publick Place,</hi> which is a Breach of the Sabbath. But when the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin</hi> it self imposeth a Command upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side what is in the Law, that is, that the Seventh day of that Feast they should appear with a Willow-bough in their hands, if this day happens on a Sabbath, then they remove the Feast aforehand to the day following: for this is their Rule, if the first day of the seventh month, called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the beginning of the year,</hi> falls on the first day, they then remove it to the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. The reason is, because then the Seventh day of that Feast would happen on the Sabbath, being the <hi>21.</hi> day of the month, when their Commandment could not be observed. And when they are ask'd the reason, why for the Command expressed in the Law they do not remove the Day, but neglect the Command; and for theirs, they remove the Day, lest their Command should
<pb facs="tcp:204172:7"/> be neglected: to this they answer, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The wise men added more strength for the maintaining their Commands, then those of the Law.</hi> For, say they, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Law is strong enough of it self, being the Command of God; but theirs, if neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, may in time come to be despised.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I could wish the people of this Nation were of this persuasion, that we might all conform to and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace those Laws that are commanded us by those that are set over us as Rulers and Directors in all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Affairs: and although it might not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether agree with our Persuasions, yet we might consider them to be wise men, and that to the best of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they do impose upon us onely such Rules as are more proper for and conducive towards our Salvation.</p>
            <p>Now, my Lord, I should much wrong my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, if I should fansie my self to have so much skill and knowledge in the Mysteries of <hi>Christianity</hi> as perhaps I may presume to have in the <hi>Judaicall</hi> Laws, in which in a manner I was born and bred. Wherefore I now here humbly crave your Lordship's Pardon, as my Lord, Father and Benefactor, if I should have laid down in this my following Discourse any thing which is not conform and agreeable to the Rules of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as it is now established: I do here utterly and absolutely disown it, and am heartily sorry for it; promising to be alwaies ready to embrace that Doctrine my Betters shall instruct me in, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Commands of your Lordship, whom all the days of my life I will be ready and prompt to obey.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordship's obedient Son and Servant, S. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure/>
            </head>
            <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>AMongst the many excellent Sentences in the Book of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> one of them is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Train up a Child in the way he should goe; and when he is old he will not depart from it.</hi> Hence comes that old Saying, <hi>Custome is a second Nature:</hi> and if so, we ought not to admire that the wisest men of the world, though they do generally agree in many Points of Science, yet that in the Principal one, which is Religion, they should be so much at a distance: for Breeding, Custom and Education do print things so firmly and strongly upon the Minds of men, that commonly they imagine it a great Sin to think any thing else to be Truth but what they have suck'd with their Mother's Milk; so that then the Doors of all Inquiry are shut. And though it be not doubted by any but that the Scriptures are the Rule of Truth; yet nevertheless men commonly are not inquisitive to contradict themselves, but rather to strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their own Opinions. And this I conceive to be the onely reason why men often differ in that very Point, in which all should endeavour to agree, being the Truth can be but one.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204172:4"/>
            <p>Some that presume to be over-wise think it a Policy and Design in those which change their Religion in which they were brought up. And this indeed is of dangerous Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, when the Change of Religion brings with it Power and Riches, which is the grand Devil of the world: for otherwise those Dissemblers must be taken to be Fools or Atheists. Others are of a quite contrary Opinion, that is, they hold Religion to be a Gift of God, and that he doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten some men with his holy Spirit, that so they may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Truth. This Opinion, in my mind, is somewhat at large on the other side; for then Reason is not to be expected: or perhaps they find so little Reason in theirs, that they will make it all Miracles; and, for ought I know, this may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease many Dissemblers. Others thinks otherwise, That whosoever shall change his Religion, if sincerely, he must be able to produce such Reasons, that the most high Professors of the same should admire him. This indeed, though more rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, is yet somewhat too high to be required: for though a man may understand some few strong and pregnant Reasons, which may be sufficient for him to know the Truth by; yet we must not doubt but those that have studied that Profession all the daies of their lives are able to illustrate it a great deal higher.</p>
            <p>And although it cannot be denied, that those that come with a sincere Heart, who shelter themselves under God's Wings, are doubtless touched by the Hand of God, being the Root whence all Good springs: yet we are to believe at the same time the Lord inlightens their Ʋnderstanding so far, as that they may be able to give a Reason for their Conversion, so that all Scruples may be taken off and vanish a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>Wherefore those few Reasons I set forth in my following Discourse you must not expect to be such, as that in them
<pb facs="tcp:204172:4"/> should be all that can be said for the illustration of Christian Religion: It will suffice if those few be strong and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. And I am confident that they are substantial enough to convince the <hi>Jews:</hi> for I may without vanity presume to have as much knowledge in the Grounds of their Religion as any other. Neither must there be here expected a very high Style: for I being a Stranger cannot possibly attain that fluent Eloquence of the <hi>English</hi> Tongue. But I hope that in these plain rude words my Sincerity may be discovered, which is all I aim at at this present; and also that the <hi>Jews</hi> may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that it was not without great reason that I embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Education be so strong a Hindrance to the discovery of the Truth, surely there must be some great persuasion that should cause a man to doubt the truth of his Opinion; and then I judge him to be upon the high Road where without any impediment he may find out the right way.</p>
            <p>That is the reason why I do inlarge my self in the proofs of particular Providence after the <hi>Jews</hi> Opinion, the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof being the first Doubt which ever I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Religion, as in my Discourse I do at large declare: and also because the <hi>Jews,</hi> considering the issue of it, would goe about to deny it, if not so amply and plainly proved before their eyes: so that I hope some of the most seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous amongst them may open their eyes, and return to the Lord.</p>
            <p>I do lastly desire, that here notice may be taken, That whereas in this my following Treatise I do quote several Passages out of the <hi>Talmud</hi> without setting forth the Books, Chapters and Leaves; the reason of it is, because the late Fire had consumed all those <hi>Hebrew</hi> Books where I could have found them: and though I might have made use of some private Libraries, which are still preserved; yet I lacked
<pb facs="tcp:204172:5"/> a Book, which I earnestly search'd for amongst all the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellers in <hi>London</hi> and the Friends I knew, and could not finde it, called <hi>Toledot Aaron,</hi> wherein (though with some pains) I might have found them out. Yet I am most sure, all that I quote is publickly known unto any of the <hi>Jews</hi> Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and all others which have full skill in that Learning: which sufficeth for our purpose, since it cannot be denied by any of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas there are several Prophecies in the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which really and truly are to be understood for <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and yet I do not make mention of them in this my Treatise; the reason is, Because the <hi>Jews</hi> of late years, merely to contradict the Christians, have studied and found out such other Expositions thereof as suffice to satisfie their mindes; and I, having full notice of them, judge that not to be the way to convince them, since they presently save them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with another interpretation. Therefore I chuse rather to argue by the way of Reason, which is undeniable to all rational men, hoping though those few Reasons be never so briefly expressed, yet upon a serious consideration the strength of them may easily appear.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204172:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Truth springing out of the Earth:</hi> THAT IS, The TRUTH of <hi>CHRIST</hi> Proved out of the EARTHLY PROMISES of the LAW.</head>
            <head>The Opinion of the <hi>Jews</hi> concerning Providence.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a certain Maxime and the generally-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Opinion amongst the <hi>Jews</hi> Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gists, and held as a fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the <hi>Mosaicall</hi> Law, That the Lord governeth onely the people of <hi>Israel</hi> with his peculiar and particular Providence, and this by the means of the Observation of the Law, taking strict notice of all their actions, and providing accordingly. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>So the Lord alone did lead him, and there was no strange God with him.</hi> He did not deal so with any other Nation, but, contrariwise, he retired himself from the Government of the World in general, leaving it to Seventy Angels as his Vicegerents, whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted as absolute Lords and Governours over the 70 Nations, into which the Children of <hi>Noah</hi> were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided after the Floud; and consequently they remained subject to the Planets and Influences of the Stars, to Chances and accidents of Fortune. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 4.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And lest thou lift up thine eyes unto heaven, and when thou seest the Sun, and the Moon, and the Stars, even all the host of Heaven, shouldest be driven to worship them and serve
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204172:10"/> them, which the Lord thy God hath divided unto all nations under the whole heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although it may seem something difficult to prove the Nations to be just 70, neither more nor less; it will suffice for our purpose, that it is the general opinion of all the ancient and modern Rabbies, grounded upon the Text <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>When the most High divided to the Nations their inheritance, when he separated the sons of Adam, he set the bounds of the people according to the number of the children of Israel.</hi> For 70 were the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel</hi> when they entred into <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 1.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And all the souls that came out of the loyns of Jacob were seventy souls: for Joseph was in Egypt already.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The said Angels, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> are entituled in the sacred Scriptures <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Elohim, Gods.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Princes, Dan.</hi> 10.13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>But the Prince of the Kingdome of Persia withstood me one and twenty days: but lo, Michael one of the chief Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces came to help me.</hi> And in the 20. verse, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Then said he, Knowest thou where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I come unto thee? and now I will return to fight with the Prince of Persia: and when I am gone forth, lo, the Prince of Greece shall come.</hi> And so he called them when he saw them intercede each one for his Nation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> say in their <hi>Midras,</hi> That the Lord doth not punish any Nation, but first he takes away the power of its Prince above: and so they understand the Text <hi>Isa.</hi> 24.21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall punish the host of the high ones that are on high, and the Kings of the earth upon the earth.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Liturgie give this Attribute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204172:10"/> unto the Lord, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>King of the Kings of Kings,</hi> intending still the said Angels.</p>
            <p>Yet they do confess that the Lord from time to time takes notice of the Actions of each Nation, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense them according to their evil or good doings: and this they call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a general Providence.</hi> This is when the sins of mankind do reach unto a high and full measure. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>But in the fourth generation they shall come hither again; for the iniquity of the Amorite is not yet full.</hi> Then it is said that the Lord comes down to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and give order for Punishment, as for example in the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because we are to treat hereafter of this matter more distinctly, we leave it to its proper place. For I will begin to shew in a right order the passages of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture whereon the <hi>Jews</hi> ground this their Opinion, since the serious consideration hereof was the first motive that inclined me to enquire the grounds of the truth of Christian Religion.</p>
            <p>AFter this manner then do the <hi>Jews</hi> establish the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World between the Lord and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Angels, whom they call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the Sane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin above:</hi> the Lord taking for himself onely the People of <hi>Israel, Deut.</hi> 32.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>For the Lord's portion is his People; Jacob is the lot of his inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they say, that soon after <hi>Adam</hi> sinned, and was cast out of Paradise, this particular Providence and Care which the Lord should have had over Man, if Sin had not hindred, began then to decline, and immediately the World remained subject to Chances and Accidents. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16,17,18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ʋnto the Woman he said, &amp;c.</hi> So that the Earth was presently filled with Pains and Troubles, and yet did not obtain the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended end, but in stead of Corn, Thorns and Thistles; as if the Lord had not that pleasure which he intended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204172:11"/> to have over Mankind: Yet notwithstanding he still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the Government of the World unto himself, as it appears in the case of <hi>Cain,</hi> where the Lord himself spoke to him, rebuked him, and declared his Banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This Assistence of the Lord in the World the <hi>Jews</hi> say lasted onely till a short space after the Floud, when the Sins of Man did reach to a high degree, committed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of their Creatour; insomuch that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest the Lord abhorred them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the Lord that he had made Man on the earth; and it grieved him at his heart.</hi> And then the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty decreed not to assist any more among men. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord said, My spirit shall not alwaies strive with man,</hi> &amp;c. Which words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>shall not strive,</hi> in the true <hi>Hebrew</hi> sense signifie, My Spirit shall not judge or govern Man. And then he declared the general Destruction of mankind, his great Mercy saving onely <hi>Noah</hi> and his three Sons, with their Wives. They all came out of the Ark; <hi>Noah</hi> offers up a Sacrifice of Thanksgiving to the Lord; there it is said, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord smelt a sweet savour, and the Lord said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man's sake; for the imagination of man's heart is evil from his youth: neither will I again smite any more every thing living, as I have done.</hi> Whence they say it appears clearly, that it seemed more convenient in the eyes of the Lord to retire to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and forsake the Government of Men, then to dwell amongst them, and be forced to destroy them ever and anon. And in the following Verse, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>While the Earth remaineth, Seed-time and Harvest, and cold and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204172:11"/> heat, and Summer and Winter, and Day and Night shall not cease.</hi> Here he established Nature, commanding it not to fail in those things without which the World could not subsist; and casting his Blessing upon mankind he retired.</p>
            <p>This Absence of the Lord from the World caused such a Disorder in it, that neither the wicked were punished, nor the just rewarded; so that Men, in stead of turning to the Lord with all their hearts, that thereby the Lord might again take care of them, and in stead of praying to God, and confessing that their Sins were the cause that their Maker was separated from them; their Malice grew so insolent, that they not onely said that the Lord did not govern the World, because Man did not deserve it, which was indeed the true reason; but the proud Ignorance of the great ones of that Time reached so far, that they publickly, though falsly, preached, that the First Cause his Government and Knowledge did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to this Low world, and that he had not, neither could have, any notice of any thing in it. And thus they published and taught, that the power over this World did belong to their new-invented Gods, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars.</p>
            <p>The ancient Rabbies say that the first inventer and maintainer of this cursed Opinion was proud <hi>Nimrod,</hi> whom the Scripture calls <hi>a mighty Hunter before the Lord,</hi> that is, one that chased Souls from the Lord. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ancient <hi>Jews</hi> say, that the wickedness of that Age reached so high, that they imagined to conquer Heaven it self; to which effect they began to build that lofty soaring Tower of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the building of this Tower was the first time where it is said that the Lord came down into the World for to take notice of Man's Actions. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord came down to see the City and the Tower which the children of men built.</hi> Wherefore his Divine Justice decreed the Division of Tongues, as it is said in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204172:12"/> 7. Verse, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Goe to, let us go down, and there confound their language,</hi> &amp;c. And because it is said here in the plural number <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>let us goe down,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> say, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>he took counsel with the Magistracy above:</hi> their meaning is, that he consulted those Angels before mentioned, whom he then constituted as Governours and Protectors over the Seventy Nations, into the which Number at that very time the World was divided. Here they say there was a necessity of them all; of the Lord, to ordain, and the Angels, to obey his Commands; for his simple Unity could not admit of any division.</p>
            <p>This Apartment of the Lord from the World lasted, say they, untill the Light of our Father <hi>Abraham</hi> began to shine in the World. He discovering the truth, how that the Creatour of all things could not infallibly but have knowledge of the most inferiour of Man's actions, and that if he did not take cognisance thereof, the fault was in Man; he began presently with a great Zeal to deny openly the power of their invented Gods, and to preach to mankind the Divine Truth, contrary to that which <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his Followers taught: For whereas they chased Souls from the Lord, <hi>Abraham</hi> did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to gain Souls to the Almighty. And so the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Rabbies understand the Text <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>and the Souls they had gotten in Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran:</hi> that is, those he had converted to the Knowledge of the most High God. For which cause the <hi>Jews</hi> say <hi>Nimrod</hi> commanded him to be cast into a Furnace of Fire, out of which the Almighty God delivered him. This, besides their Tradition, they prove out of the Text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I am the Lord that brought thee out of Ʋr of the Chaldees.</hi> These words, according to the true <hi>Hebrew</hi> sense, signifie, <hi>from the fire of the Chaldees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although by the sacred Scriptures <hi>Ʋr</hi> appears plainly to be the name of a Town in <hi>Chaldaea,</hi> the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-place
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204172:12"/> and seat of <hi>Terah, Abraham</hi>'s Father; yet they say it was so called for this very wonderfull Action, and the manifestation of the Lord there, in the deliverance of <hi>Abraham</hi> his beloved, and his Friend; which they prove after this manner: We do not find that the Lord spoke with <hi>Abraham,</hi> commanding him to forsake his native Countrey, till after his Father was dead; yet we do find that while <hi>Terah</hi> was alive it is said, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.31. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And Terah took Abraham his son—and they went forth with them from Ʋr of the Chaldees,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Terah</hi> we find died in <hi>Haran.</hi> Now if <hi>Terah</hi> out of his own free will, or for his conveniency, went forth out of <hi>Ʋr</hi> with all his Family, how then says the Lord as a great matter to <hi>Abraham, I am the Lord that brought thee forth out of Ʋr of the Chaldees,</hi> since the Lord did not command him to goe out of that place? Whence it appears to be as we have said, that is, in respect of the great Wonder the Lord wrought there for him.</p>
            <p>It seems this great Constancy in <hi>Abraham</hi> was enough to bring down from Heaven the Lord's Providence upon him, and thereby he deserved the degree of Prophecie, being led and protected in all his Actions by the most High God; that men should know that the Lord was all-sufficient, and that it was their own Sins that made a Separation between them and their God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melchizedek</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> or a perfect King, as some interpret it, when he saw <hi>Abraham</hi> with onely 318 men of his own Domesticks overcome 4 powerfull Kings, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently knew that it was by a more then humane strength, and that onely the most High could be the Authour of such a wonderfull Victory; and then he said, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Blessed be Abraham of the most high God, Gen.</hi> 14.19. Note that <hi>Melchizedek</hi> there calls the Creatour of all things <hi>the most high God,</hi> as if there were other Gods, but he was the most High. And when <hi>Moses</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:204172:13"/> in his last Song speaks of the division of the Nations, he gives the Lord the same title, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.8. For then he was retired to the most high Heaven, leaving the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Seventy Angels.</p>
            <p>This Providence continued in those times onely with the Patriarchs, and therefore the Lord was pleased to call himself <hi>the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob,</hi> (who was called <hi>Israel;</hi>) and after that <hi>the God of Israel</hi> in general; and never since that time the God of any one in particular, for all were included and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although we find that in those times the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Lord came to <hi>Abimelech</hi> and <hi>Laban,</hi> yet it was not for their own deserts, but because it was so convenient for the deliverance of his Servants: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless this Manifestation was not by the name of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the Lord,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Elohim,</hi> that is, by the mediation of their own Angel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> goes forth out of his Father's house, fearing the threatnings of his Brother <hi>Esau,</hi> and his great fear dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers that he was not certain of the most High for his guide: he lies down by the way, and the Lord appears to him in a Dream, promising him his assistence: he awakes and admires, saying, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place, and I knew it not.</hi> He rises up, and vows a Vow, which at the first sight appears somewhat difficult; for it seems that if the Lord did not accomplish for him his desires there exprest, he would not acknowledge him for his God. In answer to this the <hi>Jews</hi> say, that <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Humility did not allow him sufficient confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to believe himself the chosen one of the Lord, and that he should arrive to the attainment of that Preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence his Father and Grandfather did enjoy; and this by reason of his being born last, fearing that of right it belonged to his elder Brother, notwithstanding he had used his utmost endeavours to obtain it; insomuch that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204172:13"/> for this onely thing, if we may credit the ancient Rabbies, he struggled in the very womb with his Brother: he much doubted if the bargain of his Brother's Primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Birth-right was accepted and confirmed by the Lord, though his Brother never so much despised it: he was not sure that fraudulent way of stealing the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing intended for his Brother seem'd well in the Lord's sight. Now he finds himself in the presence of the Lord, in the house of God, and in the gate of Heaven, with more confidence he takes a Sign for himself, thereby to know whether that assistence then promised should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to him and his posterity. He considers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes; The difference which was between my Fathers and the rest of the World is, that they being subject to the changes and chances of Fortune, these were guided im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately and protected by the hand of the most High, so that their Felicities were continual and durable. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he says, If I be answered according to my Petitions and desires, <hi>Then shall the Lord be my God;</hi> that is, I shall enjoy that glory, that the Lord shall be intituled <hi>the God of Jacob</hi> as well as of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of <hi>Isaac:</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly was fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Before we proceed farther, we will take notice of the second time the Lord is mentioned to come down into the World to take cognizance of the Actions of Man, which was in the case of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> a Nation among whom but few years before the Lord had mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested himself with his great power, in working so won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull a Deliverance for them by the hand of his Servant <hi>Abraham;</hi> yet they so ungratefully provoked the Lord with their Abominations, that it is said <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I will go down now, and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know.</hi> He found them guilty, gives an account of it to his Servant <hi>Abraham,</hi> and sends an Angel to destroy them.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:204172:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Moses,</hi> say the <hi>Jews,</hi> received by tradition from his Fore-fathers this Promise which the Lord had made to them, not onely to protect them in <hi>Egypt</hi> under that Bondage, but also to govern them by himself afterwards. This is signified by that Vision <hi>Jacob</hi> saw when he went down with his Family into <hi>Egypt, Gen.</hi> 46.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I will go down with thee into Egypt, and I will also surely bring thee up again.</hi> So they say that <hi>Moses</hi> would not accept his Embassie into <hi>Egypt,</hi> untill he was first assured that the Lord himself would go along with him without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposition of any Angel: which they prove as followeth.</p>
            <p>God appears to <hi>Moses</hi> in Mount <hi>Horeb</hi> in the midst of a burning Bush: <hi>Moses</hi> wonders to see the Bush burn, and not consumed; he approaches nearer, the better to observe that wonderfull Vision: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Elohim</hi> God commands him to put off his shoes, for the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he stands is holy ground. There he is told that he who then spake with him was the God of <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> Here <hi>Moses</hi> hides his face, fearing to behold the most High, and is then commanded to goe to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and to bring the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> out of <hi>Egypt. Moses</hi> answers, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And Moses said unto God, Who am I, that I should go unto Pharaoh, and that I should bring forth the children of Israel out of Egypt?</hi> To this he is answered, Verse 12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he said, Certainly I will he with thee; and this shall be a token unto thee, that I have sent thee: When thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt, ye shall serve God upon this Mountain.</hi> According to the literal sense it seems that he did not find himself capable of so great an Employment.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Jewish</hi> Criticks interpret these words in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sense, arguing after this manner: Whatsoever is a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204172:14"/> Sign of another thing to come, it is necessary that it should precede the thing signified; and if so, how doth the Lord in this case, to certifie <hi>Moses</hi> that he should prosper in his Message, give him for a Sign, that when he had brought forth the people out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they should serve him upon that Mountain, which Sign was to succeed after their going out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Forced by this Argument they declare the Text thus, supposing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that the true Grammatical sense is infringed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: <hi>Moses,</hi> say they, was dissatisfied, doubting whether it was the Lord himself that spoke to him, or some Angel which the Divine Majesty did appoint to govern that People: and though the Lord told him, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. yet was not his Doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved; for so the Lord used to manifest himself to the other Prophets, by Dreams, Visions, or Angels, serving onely as Tongues to declare the will of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, as hereafter we shall more at large set forth.</p>
            <p>But returning to our Text, they expound it thus: What shall I be when I shall come to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and shall have brought the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> that is, In what degree or quality shall I remain after my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the one and the other thing? To the first he is answered, that when he comes to <hi>Pharaoh, Certainly I will be with thee,</hi> that is, I will assist you, and you shall prosper: and the Sign of this is, that I my self send you, I who am Eternall: and here was signified to him the name of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ehjeh,</hi> the first Attribute of the most High, which denotes his Eternity and Immutability.</p>
            <p>To the 2. Question he is answered, <hi>When thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt, ye shall serve God upon this Mountain;</hi> that is, they shall here receive the Law, (for <hi>Horeb</hi> and <hi>Sinai</hi> are both one Mountain) and he shall be the Law-giver. And because there did still remain some Scruple in <hi>Moses,</hi> imagining that he who spoke with him might be onely some high Intelligence, which, though firm and durable, might have had a beginning;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204172:15"/> he replies, <hi>If they shall say to me, What is his name? what shall I say unto them?</hi> To which he is answered, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I am that I am:</hi> though the Grammaticall sense is, <hi>I will be what I will be,</hi> that is, I will be with you what I will ever be, alwaies the same, Eternall and Immutable. And here was manifestly declared to him what before was onely signified, as hath been said.</p>
            <p>The Lord knowing well this was not enough to remove his Doubt, he proceeds farther, and says, Verse 15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And God said moreover unto Moses, Thus shalt thou say unto the Children of Israel, The Lord God of your Fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath sent me unto you: this is my name for ever, and this is my memorial unto all generations.</hi> Here was revealed to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> the mystery of the <hi>Tetragrammaton,</hi> the proper name of the absolute Creatour, the Cause of all causes, a Name which denotes him to be the onely true Being, absolute and independent in himself, without either beginning or end, which was, is, and alwaies shall be the same, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any weakness, alteration, or shadow of change; all which Properties are comprehended in this glorious Name. Then he orders <hi>Moses</hi> what to doe, assuring him that they shall hearken to his voice. <hi>Moses</hi> nevertheless requires Signs with which he might satisfie the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, lest they should not believe the Lord appeared to him. The Lord gives him Signs. And when we might ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>Moses</hi> was now abundantly satisfied, he boldly excuses himself, and says, <hi>O my Lord, I am not eloquent,</hi> &amp;c. To which the Lord yet once more replies, assuring him that he will be with him, and more particularly with his mouth; as if himself would put the words he should utter into his mouth. <hi>Who hath made man's mouth,</hi> &amp;c. And now when he had nothing left to rejoyn, he more boldly refuses his Embassie, as with an absolute denial, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204172:15"/>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he said, O my Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt send.</hi> Insomuch that the anger of the Lord was kindled against him. And when we might have expected a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere judgment to be denounced upon him, we see the Lord indulged him the greatest excellency that ever was bestow'd upon any man, Ver. 16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he shall be thy spokesman unto the people: and he shall be, even he shall be to thee in stead of a mouth, and thou shalt be to him in stead of God. Exod.</hi> 7.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord said unto Moses, See, I have made thee a God to Pharaoh; and Aaron thy brother shall be thy Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> was the end <hi>Moses</hi> aimed at: for now he was constituted absolute Lord and Governour over the Lord's People, equal in degree with the Angels above, yea and superiour to them, inasmuch as his people excelled all the rest, he spake to him face to face, and mouth to mouth, without the mediation or interposition of any Angel. <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.6,7,8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he said, Hear now my words: If there be a Prophet among you, I the Lord will make my self known unto him in a Vision, and will speak unto him in a Dream. My servant Moses is not so, who is faithfull in all mine house. With him will I speak mouth to mouth, even apparently, and not in dark speeches; and the similitude of the Lord shall he behold: wherefore then were ye not afraid to speak against my servant Moses?</hi> And although it appears that the Lord himself spake several times to the Patriarchs, yet it was alwaies, as they say, by the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Angel <hi>Michael;</hi> of whom more particularly hereafter. This, say they, is evidently proved from <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204172:16"/>
               <hi>And I appeared unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, by the name of God Almighty: but by my name Jehovah was I not known to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Moses</hi> had obtained the accomplishment of his desires, he presently receives his Instructions from the Lord, with his Letters of Credence, viz. the power of working Miracles as occasion should require. He goes to <hi>Egypt,</hi> brings the <hi>Israelites</hi> from thence, conducts them to Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Here is the third time the Lord came down. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.20. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord came down upon Mount Sinai, on the top of the Mount: and the Lord called Moses up to the top of the Mount, and Moses went up.</hi> There he gives the Law to his People, and again of new determins to assist immediately in the world amongst them; <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And let them make me a Sanctuary, that I may dwell amongst them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the mean time, whilst <hi>Moses</hi> tarried in the Mount to receive from the Lord the Orders according to which he was to govern his People, <hi>Israel,</hi> despairing of his return, concluded their Guardian-angel and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector to be lost, and as yet there remained amongst them some reliques of the Idolatry of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> with whom they had so long sojourned. They therefore ignorantly desire a Mediatour between the Lord and themselves. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And when the people saw that Moses delayed to come down out of the Mount, the people gathered themselves together unto Aaron, and said unto him, Ʋp, make us gods which shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him.</hi> They were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous, that as <hi>Aaron</hi> was Prophet to <hi>Moses</hi> their former
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204172:16"/> Mediatour, so that he would now also be their Prophet to their new-invented Gods. They presumed that <hi>Taurus,</hi> one of the Signs of the Zodiack, had some relation to and Influence over them; or perhaps the learned amongst them already knew the Oxe to be the figure of one of the four Living creatures in the Divine Chariot, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. the head and chief of all domestick Beast; and the influence of this Sign is said (the Oxe being our fellow-labourer) to respect the Plenty and increase of the Earth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Where no Oxen are, the crib is clean: but much increase is by the strength of the Oxe.</hi> So <hi>they made a Calf in Horeb, and worshipped the molten Image: Thus they changed their glory into the similitude of an Oxe that eateth grass. Psal.</hi> 106.19,20. Whereby that particular Providence called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Secinah,</hi> which dwelt amongst them and assisted them, straightway re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from them, and they were devested of that glorious Garment they attained but a few daies before at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> when the Law was proposed to them; and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their great Sin they were now made naked. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.25. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And when Moses saw that the people were naked, (for Aaron had made them naked unto their shame, amongst their enemies.)</hi> And <hi>Ex.</hi> 33.6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the children of Israel stripp'd themselves of their ornaments by the mount Horeb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Lord had decreed their utter Ruine, <hi>had not Moses his chosen stood before him in the breach, to turn away his wrath, lest he should destroy them; Psal.</hi> 106.23. and that with such ardent Zeal, that he exposes himself to destruction to save them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Yet now, if thou wilt, forgive their sin; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou hast written.</hi> Here the <hi>Jews</hi> allegorize, as if <hi>Moses</hi> should say, O Lord, when it is your decree to destroy a Nation, your custome is to recall back to your self that power you were pleased to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204172:17"/> bestow upon that Angel whom you had constituted their Governour: now since your Divine Grace hath made me immediate Governour under you over this People, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me thereby one of the number of thy holy Angels, if you will not forgive this People, I surrender up again my Patent and Commission, <hi>Blot me out of thy book which thou hast written,</hi> that is, out of thy Book wherein thou hast written my name equal with the Guardian-Angels of the other Nations of the earth.</p>
            <p>The Lord then promised him an Angel to goe along with him, and commands him to lead the People. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.2,3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And I will send an Angel before thee, and I will drive out,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for I will not go up in the midst of thee, for thou art a stiff-necked peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, lest I consume thee in the way.</hi> But <hi>Moses</hi> declines it, <hi>Ex.</hi> 33.15,16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he said unto him, If thy presence go not with me, carry us not up hence. For wherein shall it be known here, that I and thy people have found grace in thy sight? Is it not in that thou goest with us? So shall we be separated, I and thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from all the people that are upon the face of the earth.</hi> Whence the <hi>Jews</hi> conclude positively, that this is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly distinction between them and the other Nations.</p>
            <p>Here it will be convenient to take notice of a great Difficulty that ensues from this discourse, which is, that in <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20. it is written, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Behold, I send an Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared.</hi> God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises them there to send an Angel to guide and preserve them in the way, with which promise <hi>Moses</hi> seems to be well satisfied: yet <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.15. he opposes, and would not be contented, untill the Lord promised him that he would goe along with him himself, as he did before.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204172:17"/> What should then be the reason of <hi>Moses,</hi> that he should then be contented with the assistence of an Angel, when not onely himself is now dissatisfied, but the People also, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the Lord would send an Angel before them, counted it evil tidings, and mourned for it, and put not on their ornaments? <hi>Ex.</hi> 33.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And when the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned, and no man did put on him his ornaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the <hi>Jews</hi> say, that these places speak of two se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Angels, and that that Angel mentioned <hi>Ex.</hi> 33. was one of the common Angels, whom by reason of their sins the Lord would set over them, and so debase them, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them but equal with any of the other Nations, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to withdraw his particular Providence from them; as it is expresly said, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.3. <hi>For I will not go up in the midst of thee,</hi> &amp;c. But that Angel promised <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. was the Angel <hi>Michael,</hi> who is styled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Prince of the presence of God,</hi> (so he is styled <hi>Isai.</hi> 63.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Angel of his presence saved them</hi>) Lieutenant-general of the most High, and Captain of all the Celestial host, President of the Sanhedrin above, and chief Minister of the Power, Mercy and Benevolence of the Lord, Deputy of the Holy Land, Prince and Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the People of <hi>Israel. Daniel</hi> 10.21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>But I will shew thee that which is noted in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of truth, and there is none that holdeth with me in these things but Michael your Prince:</hi> and 12.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great Prince which stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the children of thy People, and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a Nation, even to that same time: and at that time thy People shall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, every one that shall be found written in the Book.</hi> (Note that <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.23. it is said <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>mine Angel,</hi> and Ver. 21. it is said <hi>my name is in him.</hi>) And farther 'tis observed, that when the Lord retired himself after the Floud from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204172:18"/> the Government of the World, as aforesaid, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was of purer eyes then to behold iniquity, and could not suffer Sin to goe unpunished. Wherefore it is written <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.3. <hi>For I will not goe up in the midst of thee,</hi> &amp;c. And concerning the Angel mentioned <hi>Ex.</hi> 23. it is said, <hi>Beware of him,</hi> &amp;c. Whence it appears that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment should have been the same with the Lord's, where men ought to be more religiously strict in their actions: for as the Care and Superintendency over them is alwaies near, so the Correction and Punishment of their Delinquency is ever at hand. Unto the Patriarchs God appeared by the name of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>El Shadai,</hi> God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that is <hi>Michael,</hi> who, as it is said, denotes the Power of the Lord; for so is the true signification of his Name, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Michael, Who is like</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>El,</hi> that is the strong and powerfull God? And though this <hi>Michael</hi> was appointed and deputed Governour of <hi>Israel,</hi> yet he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised not his Office during the life of <hi>Moses,</hi> but soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death: for when <hi>Joshua</hi> had passed over <hi>Jordan,</hi> he appeared unto him in the likeness of a man of war, <hi>Josh.</hi> 5.13,14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And it came to pass when Joshua was by Jericho, that he lift up his eyes and looked, and behold there stood a man over against him, with his sword drawn in his hand: and Joshua went unto him, and said unto him, Art thou for us, or for our adversaries? And he said, Nay, but as Captain of the Host of the Lord am I now come. And Joshua fell on his face to the earth, and did worship, and said unto him, What saith my Lord unto his servant?</hi> From those words, <hi>as Captain of the Lord's host am I now come,</hi> 'tis observed that <hi>Michael</hi> did not enter upon the execution of his Government till <hi>Moses</hi> died.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this Point; after the great sin of the golden Calf caused God to withdraw himself from them, when <hi>Moses</hi> intreated the Lord to shew him his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204172:18"/> glory, it is again said that the Lord came down in a cloud, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord descended in the cloud, and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of the Lord:</hi> and there, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> he remained untill the destruction of the first Temple; because it is not said in all that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall that the Lord either came down or went up, till <hi>Ezekiel</hi> saw him remove upon his journey in his Chariot at the very time that the Temple was destroyed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the glory of the God of Israel was gone up from the Cherub whereupon he was, to the threshold of the house, and he called to the man cloathed with linnen, which had the writer's inkhorn by his side.</hi> See more of this in the two next Chapters.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> proceed farther, and say that <hi>Balaam,</hi> the greatest and the learnedest Magician of his time amongst the Gentiles, who was the High-Priest of all their idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Rites and Ceremonies, and a maintainer of them, when he heard the report of the miraculous works <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> wrought among the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and understood that <hi>Moses</hi> for all the Doctrine he delivered alledged for his authority that the Lord appeared unto him, and that the Lord spake unto him all that he delivered to the people of <hi>Israel,</hi> and that he delivered nothing to them but what he had first received from his mouth; this <hi>Balaam</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to proclaim the same Doctrine to his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the better to strengthen and confirm them in their idolatrous Worship, avouched that the Lord also spake to him. Or perhaps he might imagine it an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility for the First Cause to speak to any man, and that it was onely a politick design in <hi>Moses</hi> to make his people believe so, the better to gain upon their affections, and to incourage their zeal and valour, and that all <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> performed was through the Art of Magick, in which <hi>Balaam</hi> was so eminently skilfull; therefore he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and presumed to have the same knowledge, or rather
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204172:19"/> more then <hi>Moses</hi> had: and so it appears by his endeavours to undoe all that <hi>Moses</hi> had done till that time.</p>
            <p>This is thus proved. <hi>Balak</hi> the son of <hi>Zippor</hi> is afraid of <hi>Israel</hi> when they approach his Borders, and sends for <hi>Balaam</hi> to curse them: <hi>Balaam</hi> arrogantly answers his Embassadors, as despising <hi>Moses,</hi> and as if the Lord had onely spoke to him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.8. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he said unto them, Lodge here this night, and I will bring you word again as the Lord shall speak unto me. And the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Moab abode with Balaam.</hi> But Ver. 9. the truth is discovered, that it was onely <hi>Elohim,</hi> which is the <hi>Angel:</hi> and the same Angel commands him Ver. 12. that he should not goe with the Messengers, nor curse the people, for they were blessed. But he proudly still persisting in his own persuasion answers the Messengers, Ver. 13. <hi>The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth to give me leave to goe with you. Balak</hi> sends to him the second time Princes more honourable then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and he, the better to declare his sincerity, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically answers, Ver. 18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And Balaam answered and said unto the servants of Balak, If Balak would give me his house-full of silver and gold, I cannot go beyond the word of the Lord my God, to doe less or more.</hi> Yet notwithstanding in the next Vers. he prays them to tarry, <hi>I pray you tarry ye also here this night:</hi> whence it appears clearly, that he himself mistrusted his own Prophecy, otherwise he durst not have presumed to tempt God, whose will he already knew. Ver. 20. <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> the Angel gives him leave to goe; but with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction not to speak any thing but what he is told. He rises as early as his Malice, solicitous to accomplish his evil intentions: and in his journey upon the way he is three times met by <hi>Michael,</hi> who is here called <hi>the Angel of the Lord.</hi> Upon which the ancient Rabbies in the <hi>Midras</hi> allegorize thus.</p>
            <p>The first time the Angel appeared to him upon the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204172:19"/> high-way, the Asse turned aside out of the way, and went into the field: Hereby is signified <hi>Abraham,</hi> that if <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> had any thing to say against his Sons, the Field was broad enough, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sons of <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Keturah;</hi> but as for the King's way, which was <hi>Isaac,</hi> he must not be touched. Next, the Angel meets him in a path of the Vineyards between two Walls: the Asse sees the Angel, and thrusts her self unto the Wall, and crushes <hi>Balaam</hi>'s foot against the Wall: That denotes <hi>Isaac,</hi> that if he had any thing against his two Sons, <hi>Esau</hi> would hardly be granted him, but <hi>Jacob</hi> must not be touched. The third time the Angel meets him in a narrow place where was no way to turn either to the right hand or to the left, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>Jacob,</hi> whose Sons were all chosen of God, and with them no fault to be found: and here the Asse fell down under <hi>Balaam,</hi> the Lord permitting the dumb Asse to speak with man's voice, and forbid the madness of this Prophet, and to shew him how extravagant his Wickedness and Pride was, the most abject and servile of all Beasts being more capable of God's Providence then himself.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Balaam</hi>'s eyes were opened, finding experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally the truth <hi>Moses</hi> professed, since he himself saw the Angel of the Lord, who spoke to him, and bid him goe on his journey, he still endeavouring to find a way to curse <hi>Israel:</hi> and although what had already happened to him might seem sufficient to alter his purpose, yet he well knew he who spoke to him was a created Angel, though of a far higher degree then those he formerly conversed with: or perhaps he might discover him to be <hi>Michael,</hi> the Prince and Advocate of <hi>Israel,</hi> that, interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for his own People, came to prevent that Curse he intended them; wherefore he yet gave not such full credit to the authority of that Vision, as to desist from his purpose.</p>
            <p>Now he comes to <hi>Balak,</hi> prepares his Sacrifices, goes to his Divinations, orders his Enchantments, and <hi>Elohim</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:204172:20"/> appears to him, but with greater authority, for he puts the Lord's word into his mouth, so that in stead of cursing he blesses <hi>Israel. Balak</hi> reproves him: he saw himself gradually ascending to the highest degree of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, therefore answers <hi>Balak,</hi> that he must <hi>speak what the Lord puts into his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the <hi>Jews</hi> observe God's great love towards his People, in that he not onely crowns them with Blessings and Felicities, but also forces their Adversaries to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to them. Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> wrestling with his Brother <hi>Esau</hi>'s Guardian-Angel prevails over him, and will not let him goe, till he had confirm'd those Blessings to him which the World imagined he had fraudulent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken from his Brother: wherefore the Angel chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges his name <hi>Jacob,</hi> signifying to <hi>supplant</hi> or <hi>deceive,</hi> into <hi>Israel,</hi> which signifies <hi>the righteous one of God;</hi> as if he had said, It is right and just before God, what the World esteemed a Deceit and Fraud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Balaam</hi> now again prepares his <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and proceeds with his Enchantments, and the Lord himself meets him, and puts a word in his mouth, Chap. 23. ver. 16. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the beginning of this Prophecy, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>God is not a man, that he should lie, neither the son of man, that he should repent: hath he said, and shall he not doe it? or hath he spoken, and shall he not make it good?</hi> As if he should say, Till now I gave not full credit to what I heard, as not knowing it to be the will of the most High: but now I have heard it from his own mouth, and as he himself is immutable, so his Sentence must be firm. Note that this word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>El</hi> in the singular number is never spoken of any but the most High.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Balak</hi> strives again the third time to procure a Curse against <hi>Israel, Balaam</hi> went not, as at other times, to seek for Enchantments, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.1. Hereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he was fully satisfied that the Word of the Lord is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204172:20"/> unalterable; and sensible of the superlative dignity he had obtained in speaking to the Lord mouth to mouth, as <hi>Moses</hi> did, he boasts of himself Ver. 3, 4. <hi>Balaam the son of Beor hath said,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He hath said which heard the words of God,</hi> &amp;c. and Ver. 16. <hi>He who knew the knowledge of the most High,</hi> &amp;c. Whence the ancient Rabbies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Text, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And there arose not a Prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom the Lord knew face to face.</hi> In <hi>Israel</hi> there did not arise a Prophet like unto <hi>Moses,</hi> but among the Nations there did, and that was <hi>Balaam:</hi> meaning that <hi>Balaam</hi> arrived to as high a degree of Prophecie as <hi>Moses</hi> did, that the confirmation of <hi>Israel</hi>'s Blessings might flow from the same fountain the Blessings first sprang from, and that the Nations might know that the Lord is willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow his greatest Favours upon such as are capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them, and that it is Sin onely that can separate between the Lord and a People.</p>
            <p>For this cause also it is said that the Book of <hi>Job</hi> was inserted in the Canon of the Holy Scripture, insomuch that there is an Opinion in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> that there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver such a man as <hi>Job,</hi> but that the Book was made onely for a Parable. However, the generally-received Opinion is, that there was really such a man as <hi>Job,</hi> the Prophets making mention of him, and that he lived in <hi>Moses</hi> his time, and that <hi>Moses</hi> wrote this Book for the consolation of the Nations, and to shew them that, if their Merits were great enough, they might attract to themselves so much of the power of God, as to suffice to divert all the Evils and Judgments the malignity of the Planets should threaten them with. For as the Lord is said to come down from time to time to take cognizance of the extraordinary Wickedness of the Nations, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to inflict his Punishments; so he takes care to reward and justifie them when they deserve it, as in the case of <hi>Niniveh:</hi> his Justice for their sins decreed to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204172:21"/> destroy the City in 40 days; yet upon their Humiliation and Repentance he revokes the Decree, his Mercie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails, he forgives them, and is reconciled to them.</p>
            <p>Note that here the Lord is not said to come down, the first Temple then standing, where his Presence dwelt.</p>
            <p>Before we goe farther, I think it convenient to set down the constant Opinion of the <hi>Jews</hi> concerning the Nations of the World, and the obligations lying upon them for their attainment of Felicity.</p>
            <p>Seven Commands God laid upon the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> and they call them the <hi>Seven Precepts of the Sons of Noah,</hi> to the observation of which all men throughout the World are equally bound.
<list>
                  <item>The first is, Not to blaspheme the Name of the Lord.</item>
                  <item>2. To abstain from Idolatry; by which is meant, not to give Divine Worship to any Being beside the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</item>
                  <item>3. To doe no Murther.</item>
                  <item>4. Not to commit Adultery.</item>
                  <item>5. Not to steal.</item>
                  <item>6. Not to eat part of any Beast while the Beast lives.</item>
                  <item>7. To establish Judges, to doe Justice to all men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Besides the general Tradition, they prove it thus, The first two Precepts, of reason, right and justice, belong to the most high Lord and Creatour of all things. Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Theft occasioned the Deluge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Earth was filled with violence;</hi> and Ver. 12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>All flesh had corrupted his way upon the earth:</hi> this is by all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of Adultery, yet comprehending under it all the several <hi>species</hi> of Uncleanness. The other three were given to <hi>Noah</hi> expresly after the Floud. The sixth Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>not to eat a part of any living creature,</hi> is proved from <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>But flesh with the life thereof, which is the bloud thereof, shall you not eat.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:204172:21"/> The other two, <hi>to doe no Murther,</hi> and <hi>to doe Justice,</hi> are included in one Text, Ver. 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Whoso sheddeth man's bloud, by man shall his bloud be shed:</hi> where as God forbids Murther, so he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powers Judges to take cognizance of it, if commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>True it is, the first five Precepts were or ought to have been observed before the Floud; for Murther is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Violence:</hi> for if Violence is forbid to be offer'd to the Goods of a man, then much more to the Life of a man. So that properly onely the two last were commanded to <hi>Noah,</hi> (to the other five he was pre-obliged:) for till <hi>Noah</hi>'s time Flesh was unlawfull to be eaten, but now a License is granted him to eat flesh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you,</hi> &amp;c. yet with this Proviso, not to eat part of any living beast. As for the last Precept, <hi>to set up Judges,</hi> it was now given: for before, God governing the World by himself, by himself he executed Justice upon Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents; but after the Floud, retiring himself from the World, he impowers men in his stead to execute Justice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Offenders. And the observation of these Precepts they say is sufficient to Salvation accordingly. It is asserted in the <hi>Talmud,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The good ones of the Nations shall have a portion in the World to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we return to <hi>Job,</hi> who was a perfect and upright man, one that <hi>feared God, and eschewed evil,</hi> one of the Nations of the Earth, of the Land of <hi>Ʋz,</hi> a religious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> of the Seven Precepts of <hi>Noah;</hi> yet born under so malignant a Planet, that we see he suffered the loss of all he had, and his Afflictions in Body so great, that he chose strangling rather then life.</p>
            <p>The Sanhedrin above, styled the Sons of God, were convened, and present themselves before the Lord, each one to give an accompt of the particular Nations and People committed to their Protection. Satan the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204172:22"/> Adversary and Accuser of all Mankind, comes also among them. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Satan, the evil inclination of man, and the Angel of death, are one and the same.</hi> The Lord then asks Satan concerning <hi>Job,</hi> as it were glorying and triumphing in his excellencies, <hi>Hast thou considered my servant Job,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. Satan answers, Ver. 9, 10, 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Then Satan answered the Lord, and said, Doth Job fear God for nought? Hast not thou made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he hath on every side? thou hast blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land. But put forth thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, and he will curse thee to thy face.</hi> As if he had said, What praises deserves <hi>Job,</hi> since you have filled him with all the Felicities the World can afford, and hast so made a hedge about him, that the Planetary Influences of Heaven cannot touch him, but he remains secure against all their malevolent Aspects? Now if you please to leave him to himself, he will desert your Worship, and forsake your Service, and blaspheme your name. The Lord puts into his power all that <hi>Job</hi> had, onely with this reserve, that he should not put forth his hand against his person. Satan accordingly does, and destroys all he had, even to his Sons and Daughters: and he, as unconcern'd, bears it patiently, and without frowardness says, <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away: blessed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Satan, seeing he could not conquer <hi>Job</hi>'s Fortitude and holy Resolutions, prepares a second Plea against the next Convention; where being asked again whether he had considered <hi>Job,</hi> he replies, <hi>Job</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued nothing but his Life: if his bones and flesh were touched, he would blaspheme him to his face. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Lord said, <hi>Behold, he is in thy hand; but save his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204172:22"/> life.</hi> Whence it appears, that the malign Influence of the Planets reached to his Life, since the Lord was in a manner constrained to bind up their Influences, and give Satan a positive decree to save him. Satan now confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to succeed in his enterprize, after he had smitten him with a grievous and loathsome Disease, remembring <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, possessed <hi>Job</hi>'s Wife, who frowardly says to him, <hi>Dost thou still retain thine integrity? curse God, and die.</hi> What is the Almighty, that we should serve him? and what profit should we have if we pray unto him? since he multiplies so many Mischiefs upon us, one crowding upon the back of another, and such storms of Miseries, so sharp and so violent, that the least of them surmounts the horrid pangs of Death. Blaspheme, that you may die, and thus end your Tortures. She knew that the transgression of every Precept of <hi>Noah</hi> should be punished with death, but especially Blaspheming the Name of God. Yet <hi>Job</hi> would not leave his Integrity, to give an opportunity for Satan to prevail over him, and replies, <hi>Shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive evil?</hi> As much as to say, The Lord is almighty, and doth what he pleases both in Heaven and Earth; he made us, we owe him our being; he is not beholden to us, our righteousness extends not to him, his Will is his Law. And hence he concludes, that the Lord doth not govern this World, and that all the Mischiefs and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles he suffered proceeded from the malignity of the Planets, who were deputed the Administrators and Rulers thereof: for after his sad Silence seven days, the first of his speech was to curse his Nativity, <hi>Job.</hi> 3.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the night in which it was said, There is a man-child conceived.</hi> And that whole Chapter is a Scheme of man's Misery, and to shew that it had been better for him not to have been born at all, or, being born, quickly to have turned out of the world again and died.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:204172:23"/>
            <p>The <hi>Jewish</hi> Expositors observe from <hi>Job</hi> 2.10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>In all this did not Job sin with his lips,</hi> hitherto, in all this <hi>Job</hi> sinned not, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he did: not imagining that the Lord did not govern the World, as <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his followers did; but that though he might, he refused to doe it, his supreme Majesty being transcendent, and all Sublunary things too mean and too unworthy for his Superintendeney or Inspection, which provokes him to say, <hi>Job</hi> 7.17. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>What is man, that thou shouldst magnifie him, and that thou shouldst set thine heart upon him? Job</hi> 23.13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>But he is in one mind, and who can turn him? and what his Soul desireth, even that he doth.</hi> That is, His greatness is so immense, that none can oppose or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his will; so that man's Actions are not at all directed by him, his eternal happiness takes no notice of them. <hi>Job</hi> 9.22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>This is one thing, therefore I said it, He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyeth the perfect and the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which seduced <hi>Job</hi> into this Opinion was, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering his own Justice, together with the extremity of his Calamities. <hi>Job</hi> 27.6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it goe: my heart shall not reproach me so long as I live.</hi> The flourishing also of the Wicked confirmed him in this Heresy. <hi>Job</hi> 21.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though it must not be denied that all these things happen in this World of woe, this Vale of misery; yet there is another World to come, a World of Retribution, where all things shall be weighed in a just balance, and accordingly recompensed. <hi>Psal.</hi> 92.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>When the wicked spring as the grass, and when all the workers of iniquity do flourish; it is that they shall be destroyed for ever.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:204172:23"/> This whole Psalm is understood of the World to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> being a Gentile, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> to whom the Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God were not revealed, knew of no other World then this, as appears <hi>Job</hi> 7.9,10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>As the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away: so he that goeth down to the grave shall come up no more. He shall return no more to his house, neither shall his place know him any more. Job</hi> 14.7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>For there is hope of a tree, if it be cut down, that it will sprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not cease. Though the root thereof wax old in the earth, and the stock thereof die in the ground: Yet through the sent of water it will bud, and bring forth boughs like a plant. But man dieth and wasteth away: yea, man giveth up the ghost, and where is he? As the waters fail from the Sea, and the floud decaieth and drieth up: So man lieth down, and riseth not till the heavens be no more; they shall not awake, nor be raised out of their sleep. O that thou wouldst hide me in the grave, that thou wouldst keep me in secret, untill thy wrath be past, and thou wouldst appoint me a set time, and remember me! If a man die, shall he live again? all the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</hi> And when his Friends strongly opposed this persuasion, and, believing that the Lord still governed the World, urge that his Sins were the onely cause of his Misery; <hi>Job,</hi> considering the slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grounds they had for this belief, rebukes them for endeavouring to vindicate God, without sufficient reason to convince the Doubter. <hi>Job</hi> 13.7,8,9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:204172:24"/>
               <hi>Will you speak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him? Will ye accept his person? will ye contend for God? Is it good that he should search you out? or as one man mocketh another, do ye so mock him?</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> was so highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked with their bitter reflexions upon him, that he charged God foolishly. <hi>Job</hi> 27.2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>As God liveth, who hath taken away my judgement, and the Almighty, who hath vexed my soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length his three Friends ceased from speaking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was just in his own eyes. Then the noble <hi>Elihu</hi> began to speak, <hi>Job</hi> 32.2,3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>His wrath was kindled against Job, because he justified himself rather then God. Also against his three Friends was his wrath kindled, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job.</hi> Then directing his speech more particularly to <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 35.2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Thinkest thou this to be right, that thou saydst, My righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is more then God's?</hi> he also asserts to him, that man may lose his understanding in going to search out Divine Mysteries by a natural Light, the excellency of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may destroy the Sense, and weak eyes must not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to gaze upon the Sun: to find out the Cause by the Effects is a difficult progression; but when we know the Cause, the Effects may easily be discovered. So that the evidence of Divine matters must necessarily come by Revelation, and not by the curious search of humane wisedome. Therefore he says, <hi>Job</hi> 33.15,16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falleth upon men, in slumberings upon the bed: Then he openeth the ears of men, and sealeth their instruction.</hi> He proceeds farther, to prove that God often tries just men, that the constancy of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204172:24"/> Graces might be an example for the World's conformity, verse 19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>He is chastned also with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with strong pain.</hi> And Verse 28. he discovers to him the Immortality of the Soul. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>He will deliver his soul from going into the pit, and his life shall see the light.</hi> Verse 30. he declares the Resurrection. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>To bring back his soul from the pit, to be enlightned with the light of the living.</hi> How is it then that <hi>Job</hi> did say, <hi>I am righteous, and God hath taken away my judgment? Job</hi> 34.5.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Elihu</hi> had concluded, <hi>Job</hi> was convinc'd to si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and replied not again: and God himself confirms presently what <hi>Elihu</hi> had spoken, and charges <hi>Job</hi> for censuring his Divine Justice, and determining the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Heaven, when the highest perfections of Reason with the most diligent inquisition cannot attain the true knowledge of natural Causes. To whom <hi>Job</hi> makes his humble confession, Chap. 42.2,3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I know that thou canst doe every thing, and that no thought can be withholden from thee. Who is he that hideth counsel without knowledge? therefore have I uttered that I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood not, things too wonderfull for me, which I knew not.</hi> and in the 6. Ver. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Wherefore I abhor my self, and repent in dust and ashes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it here then be considered how acceptable it is to God, for vain man, that would be wise, and yet is but like a wild Asse's Colt, to presume to discourse of Divine Mysteries, and to determine them, though they be the most undoubted Truths in the world; when they are so far from being able to give a reason for them, that they have nothing to convince the gainsayers. Here we see <hi>Job</hi>'s three Friends pleading against <hi>Job</hi> in the behalf of God; he denying their Positions, because he found not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204172:25"/> their Reasons sufficient to convince him: and yet <hi>Job</hi> 42.7,8 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends: for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath. Therefore take unto you now seven Bullocks and seven rams, and goe to my servant Job, and offer up for your selves a burnt-offering, and my servant Job shall pray for you; for him will I accept: lest I deal with you after your folly, in that ye have not spoken of me the thing which is right, like my servant Job.</hi> So that one may venture to say, An Errour grounded upon good reason, where there is no intention to deceive, but rather a solicitous inquiry after Truth, may as soon find pardon from the indulgence of Heaven, as a Truth taken up at peradventures, and as ill defended as it was casually found, may reap acceptance. Truths imbezzled by bold and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Assertors frequently confirm the opposite Hereticks, and too often give occasion for the Truth to be evil spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and God's Name to be blasphemed: whilst a modest and innocent Errour, abetted with good probable Arguments, will quicken every ingenuous mind to a stricter scrutiny, that it is more then probable the Truth may be discovered, and embraced too, by him who first defended the contrary.</p>
            <p>SInce it appears then by what hath been said, that God's particular Providence was onely among the <hi>Jews;</hi> we shall now proceed to declare how the <hi>Jews</hi> framed to themselves a new Modell of the World, adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receive and continue this Divine Influence which they call <hi>Schecina</hi> amongst them.</p>
            <p>As they generally divide the World into three parts;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204172:25"/> the Angelicall World, assisting about the Throne of God, the Celestial World, respecting the Sphears, and this Sublunary and Elementary World: so the House of God was distinguished into three parts or three degrees of Holiness gradually separated, semblably thereto; that is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Palace,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Outer Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Holy of Holies</hi> represented the Angelical World. And because the Glory of the Lord is more eminently resident among those blessed Spirits, therefore the Ark of the Testament, representing the First Cause, was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced therein: and since the Lord and his Will are one, therefore the two Tables of Stone, containing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue, which is the manifestation of his Will, were also laid up there: and this being the occasion of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or Displeasure, there were also put there the Pot of <hi>Manna</hi> and the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> representing Reward or Punishment to the Observers or Transgressors of it. This Ark was covered, to shew the Incomprehensibility of the First Cause; and covered with pure Gold, to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Firmness and Duration of the First Being. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Covering were two Cherubims of Gold also, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Angels: made of the same Piece with the Covering, to represent that they immediately proceeded from the Lord. They were of Gold, to shew their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy in performing the Will of their Maker; together with their Duration: they were Male and Female, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying their gradual Difference one from another; some Angels receiving immediately from the Lord, others from their superiour Order. Wherefore the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphrase, <hi>Isai.</hi> 6. renders these words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>One cried unto another,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>One received from another.</hi> Their Faces looking one towards another denoted, that they revealed and communicated what they received from the Lord one to another. They look towards the Covering, to shew that they expected to derive all their Felicity from the Lord. They had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204172:26"/> Wings, to shew their Swiftness and Agility in God's ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: these Wings covered not onely their Bodies, but also all the Covering, to represent that they were hidden from all creatures below them, so that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend their Essence. There was also an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar over-laid with Gold, of which we shall speak hereafter.</p>
            <p>Next this was the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Palace,</hi> representing the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall or Sphericall World, which, because it was corpore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, was separated from the Holy of Holies by a Veil, as being of another quality and matter. Because the Sun, Moon and Stars, to whom the Dominion over the Elementary World is given, are there, in this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was a Table placed, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present their Majesty and Power. Upon this Table were set twelve Loaves in two rows, six on a row, representing the twelve Signs of the Zodiack. These Loaves were called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. Loaves of Faces;</hi> as if the Misery or Felicity of this World depended upon their Influence. They were changed every week, to shew the diversity of their Effects, according to the various Transits of the Seven Planets, which were represented by the golden Candlestick with seven Lights, placed here also: the middle Light onely burning upwards representing the Sun; the rest, three of each side, bowed and inclined to it, to shew that they borrowed their light from the Sun.</p>
            <p>Next was the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Outer Court,</hi> representing this Sublunary World. It was in the open Air, without any Covering, to shew the several Inconveniences this World is obnoxious to. Here was the Altar placed, Beasts were kill'd and offered upon it, to shew the power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Death. So that in this little World the <hi>Jews</hi> say God dwelt, to provide all things necessary for them: and here he dwelt till the Destruction of it, as appears from the 9, 10, 11. Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> when he saw the Lord in his Chariot leaving this World, and ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into Heaven again. And so they resolve a Question arising from the difference of the Vision of <hi>Isaiah</hi> and this in <hi>Ezekiel. Isaiah</hi> describes the Cherubims with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204172:26"/> six Wings, two whereof covered their faces, and two their feet, and with the other two they flew: here <hi>Ezekiel</hi> describes them onely with four Wings, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribes the form of their feet, which <hi>Isaiah</hi> doth not. They reconcile this Doubt thus. The two middle Wings signifie, as hath been said, their expeditious Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to execute the Will and Decrees of God; the two upper Wings were the receptacles of the Emanations of the Divine Influx; the two lower Wings were as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit-pipes to convey the Influence they received from above into the Lower World. <hi>Isaiah,</hi> living in the time the Temple stood, saw them with all their Wings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting this Indulgence of Heaven, and communicating to Man the Goodness of the Lord: but <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> at the Destruction of the Temple, saw them onely with four Wings, to intimate that these Conduit-pipes were now stopped, God then retiring out of the World, and deserting the Government thereof.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Babylonish</hi> Captivity, when <hi>Ahashuerus</hi> reigned over <hi>Persia,</hi> happened that great Deliverance of the <hi>Jews</hi> by the means of <hi>Mordecai</hi> and <hi>Esther,</hi> which they value little inferiour to their coming out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of which they ordained and took upon them and upon their Seed to keep two days yearly, which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly observed by them throughout all places in the World where they inhabit, untill this day: and it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired why in all this History the name of <hi>God</hi> is not once mentioned; for which this is the reason: Because the Deliverance happened after the Lord had absented himself from the World; this wonderfull Action was wrought by the hand of the Angel of <hi>Persia,</hi> whom the Lord caused to disturb the King in his sleep, that he might come to know how much he was beholden to <hi>Mordecai,</hi> as the History at large reports, and because the Lord did not immediately appear in it, his great Name could not be there mentioned.</p>
            <p>The conclusion of the whole matter is this. The <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:204172:27"/> do believe that the immediate Providence of the Lord was never yet enjoy'd by any Nation except their own; and that if the Lord hath at any time taken notice of any other Nation or Person, either to reward or punish them, it was in respect of their strict Observance or Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Seven Precepts of <hi>Noah,</hi> to which Canon the Lord obliged all mankind. Then, according to their Opinion, it must necessarily follow, that what-ever Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth not observe that Canon, or pretends to serve the Lord any other way, their Worship is erroneous, and cannot be accepted, and consequently cannot obtain the Divine Providence. Now if we can evidently prove that the Lord appeared to the Christians in the same manner as he did formerly to the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> who can doubt but their Religion and manner of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is accepted of the Lord, since otherwaies they could not possibly enjoy this so great Preeminence?</p>
            <p>And because we see many things strangely succeed casually and accidentally, insomuch that the wisest of men may be deceived by them, and judge them acts of Providence; it will be but necessary to give some Rules whereby Chance may be distinguished from Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Thus then I say, That which is ordered by and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God must necessarily concur and agree in all its parts equally, without intermixture of any thing that is of different purpose. So that that Reward or Punishment which the Lord appoints must be adequate and proper to the Merit or Demerit of the Act done. This is the cause, say Expositors, why <hi>Jethro</hi> became a Convert. He had seen the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ungratefull in forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Preservation they owed to <hi>Joseph</hi>'s Prudence; how, not contented with the iron Slavery they held the <hi>Israelites</hi> under, their male Children now must be cast into the <hi>Nile:</hi> and notwithstanding the Lord wrought so many wonderfull Miracles among them, all would not suffice to make <hi>Jethro</hi> forsake his idolatrous Priesthood to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204172:27"/> the Gods of <hi>Midian.</hi> But hearing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Horsemen and Chariots were drown'd in the Red sea, he says, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Now know I that the Lord is greater then all gods: for in the thing wherein they dealt proudly he was above them.</hi> They sinned by Water, and by Water their Sin was avenged. Now he is a Convert to the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> and believes his Providence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eli</hi> the Priest governs <hi>Israel,</hi> and for the Sin of his Sons God hides his face from his people; the <hi>Philistins</hi> catch at the opportunity, and not onely prevail against them, but also captivate the Ark, then, by reason of their Sins, like a dead Carkass without a Soul informing it. They, proud with this success, return triumphantly, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting their way to the Temple of their God <hi>Dagon,</hi> which is <hi>Neptune,</hi> present and dedicate their noble Spoil there, as if their invented <hi>Dagon,</hi> God of the Sea, had prevailed over the great Creatour of Heaven and Earth, the Sea and all that therein is. Then the Lord, for his Name's sake profaned in that Nation, observes their Pride, and punishes them with <hi>Haemorrhoids,</hi> a Disease naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a Melancholick humour. When they saw how in the height of their Revellings and rejoycings, and their Thanksgiving-offerings, they were so cruelly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, they considered, though lately, that this evil was preternatural. Filled as much with fear as pain, they resolved to send back the Ark of the Lord of <hi>Israel;</hi> and after they had consulted all their Priests and their Wise men, they mutually agree to experiment whether those present Evils did really proceed from the Lord, or from Chance. They say, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7,8,9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:204172:28"/>
               <hi>Now therefore make a new cart, and take two milch-kine, on which there hath come no yoak, and tie the kine to the cart, and bring their calves home from them: And take the Ark of the Lord, and lay it upon the cart, and put the jewels of gold which ye return him for a Trespass-offering in a coffer by the side thereof, and send it away, that it may goe. And see, if it goeth up by the way of his own coast to Beth-shemesh, then he hath done us this great evil: but if not, then we shall know that it is not his hand that smote us; it was a chance that happened to us.</hi> Whereby it appears they would not be satisfied untill they saw all circumstances adjust and agree together.</p>
            <p>LEt the Church of <hi>Christ</hi> now be seriously consider'd from its Original, and certainly we shall find an immense and fathomless Love and Providence alwaies protecting them. What Patience, without the admirable Assistence of the Lord, could have so magnanimously undergone those unutterable Troubles and Persecutions they underwent, insomuch that their Adversaries and Torturers were struck with astonishment? What Constancy and Perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can compare to theirs? Under how many insul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Pharaohs</hi> have they been oppressed, and out of as many <hi>Egypts</hi> redeemed? It is beyond the belief or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of possibility, <hi>had not the right hand of the Lord led them, and the Angel of his face saved them,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving them till they arrived to that height where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they now stand, for the glory of his Name's sake. <hi>They grew up like a tender plant before him, and as a root out of a dry ground, Isai.</hi> 53.2. Which whole Chapter I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe may be truly interpreted for the Church of <hi>Christ:</hi> and I am sure the <hi>Jews</hi> have nothing to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose against it.</p>
            <p>Hath not the Lord manifested himself with his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular care over them in all Ages? Who is so brutish and devoid of Reason, that doth not consider the miraculous Restauration of our Sovereign Lord King <hi>CHARLES?</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:204172:28"/> The wonderfull circumstances thereof are so universal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, I need not instance in the particulars. How could this be brought to pass without the particular as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistence of the Lord of hosts? <hi>Surely it is the Lord's doing, and it is wonderfull in our eyes.</hi> Who but the God of Battels could have brought him in without one drop of bloud, and this to the face of so many thousands of his enemies? All natural means possible were endeavoured, and yet frustrate in the issue: but <hi>When a man's ways please the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> Who can doubt but in that wonderfull Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in the <hi>Royal Oak</hi> the Lord had a particular Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendencie over him, and a design by his Restauration to convince the ambitious Pride and raging madness of them who durst contrive, act or abett any thing derogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Sacred Majesty?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joseph</hi> maliciously banish'd from his mournfull Father's house, when he presumes to find rest in <hi>Potiphar</hi>'s Service, is condemned to an eternall Dungeon; where he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to serve two Prisoners, <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Butler and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. There he interprets them their Dreams, which came to pass accordingly. And though the Lord during his whole Exile shew'd him tokens of Love; yet he, like a man, mistakes, and fixes all his confidence on the Butler. But the Lord's actions are beyond the scrutiny of Nature, and their lustre would be debased, if by natural means discover'd. See the conclusion of the matter: The Butler did not remember <hi>Joseph,</hi> but forgat him. The duplication of the phrase seems to argue that his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulness was forced upon him from above, to shew thereby, that in <hi>Joseph</hi>'s Deliverance no man should have a share, God himself would doe it. Parallel to this runs the Deliverance of our Lord the KING. God asserts it wholly to himself, without the partnership of humane strength; <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my spirit, saith the Lord of hosts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I seriously considered this miraculous act of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204172:29"/> I was confounded in my spirit, not being able to apprehend how it was possible this Nation should enjoy that Prerogative and Privilege, which was denied all other Nations, and reserved onely for the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> since, as I conceived, they did not serve the Lord in a way that he would accept: and although this was not sufficient at that time to convince me, yet the thoughts thereof did so much possess my mind, that the more I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to study Arguments to reconcile me to my self, the more I grew dissatisfied; till at length it pleased the Lord to touch my heart, and in a full resolution I devested my self of my former <hi>Mosaical</hi> Zeal, that without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice I might more seriously inquire the Truths of Christianity; since I now saw them cloathed in the same Garments with the Children of <hi>Israel.</hi> And in this great distraction and thoughtfulness the Lord permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to arrive to a safe Port, where I happily cast An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor: so that where all the World was lost, I may safely say I found my Salvation. I then argued with my self after this manner.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> infallibly believe the Soul to be intellectual and immortal, called by them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>neshamah, Breath,</hi> an individuall Substance, perfect, clean and pure, before it came down into the World, proceeding from God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And he breathed into his nostrills the breath of life:</hi> and that after it is separated from the Body, it remains in its own being, and then receives reward or punishment according to what it hath done in the Body. They also believe the Resurrection of the Body so firmly, that they say in the <hi>Talmud,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>He that says the Resurrection of the Body is not declared in the Law, hath no part in the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though this is manifest to all who have knowledge of the <hi>Jews</hi> Creed, yet we will prove, for the satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them who are strangers to it, that this Article is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204172:29"/> received amongst them all without any one's contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting it; and that by the express words of their Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, universally accepted, as compiled and instituted by <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe and the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> of his time, called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the men of the great Assembly.</hi> The first words of their Morning-prayer are, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>My God, the Soul which thou hast given within me is clean, thou hast created it, thou hast formed it, thou hast breathed it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and thou dost preserve it within me, and thou wilt take it from me, and return it to me in the World to come: all the time the Soul is within me, I confess before thee, my Lord, and the God of my Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. Hereby it is evident they believe the Soul to be a Substance of it self, and that there shall be a Resurrection; and for farther proof, they alwaies pray for the better state of the Soul after its Separation. <hi>Maimon</hi>'s last three Articles of their thirteen are, that they must believe Reward and Punishment after Death, the Advent of the <hi>Messias,</hi> and the Resurrection.</p>
            <p>I think here it will not be amiss to discover their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the <hi>Messias,</hi> so many Ages by them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that he shall be a man born of the Line of <hi>David,</hi> who shall rise in the latter end of their Captivity, whom the Lord shall endue with so much Power, Grace and Favour, that he shall prosper in all his actions, shall gather them from all Nations whither they are scattered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them to their own Land, build them a new Temple, that Sacrifices may be there offered as formerly; final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that then all the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> shall be observed, all the Commandments, Judgments and Statutes therein contained, that so they and their Children may live happily in this World even to the very day of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204172:30"/> when Death, the Curse which <hi>Adam</hi> by his Transgression entail'd upon all his Posterity, shall be no more. All this as concerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            <p>As to the Gentiles, they believe that upon his entrance into his Kingdom, many Nations shall be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon their Land, to fight against him, to impede his Designs. This is the War of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> where the Lord will so highly manifest himself with so many Judgments upon these Nations, that they shall suffice to proclaim his Name throughout all the World, and the <hi>Messias,</hi> his Anointed, to be Lord and Emperour over all the Earth. And that then all Nations shall abhor their Idolatries and false Worship, turning to the Lord with all their hearts, confessing and acknowledging him to be the onely God. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 16.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>O Lord, my strength and my fortress, and my refuge in the day of affliction, the Gentiles shall come unto thee from the ends of the earth, and shall say, Surely our fathers have inherited lies, vanity, and things wherein there is no profit.</hi> Then they shall all observe and keep the Seven Precepts of <hi>Noah.</hi> For, as the ancient Rabbins say, no Proselyte shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived after the <hi>Messias</hi> is come: accordingly, in the most solemn Day in the year, the day of Atonement, they pray for the Conversion of the Nations, in these words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Therefore we hope to thee, O Lord our God, to see suddenly the glory of thy strength to take away all Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204172:30"/> from the Earth, and that Idols shall be utterly cut off, that the World may be settled through the Kingdom of the Almighty, and all the sons of Flesh may call upon thy Name, and all the wicked ones of the earth may look towards thee; that all the inhabitants of the world may know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that to thee every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear: before thee, O Lord our God, they shall bow and fall down, and give honour to the glory of thy Name; and all of them shall with pleasure receive the yoak of thy Kingdom, and thou shalt reign over them for ever: for the Kingdom is thy own, and for evermore thou shalt reign with glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore they say, one Precept shall be added to them above the Seven, which is the keeping of the Feast of Tabernacles, as they interpret <hi>Zachary</hi> 14. the <hi>Talmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dists</hi> delivering, that the Nations were all of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Feast, for they were commanded in the Week of that Feast to offer up 70 Bullocks in behalf of the 70 Nations, <hi>Numb.</hi> 29. this Feast representing the universal Peace which the whole World shall then enjoy. Then the power shall be taken away from the Seventy Angels, and God will reassume it to himself as at the Creation. <hi>Isai.</hi> 54.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>For thy maker is thine husband, (the Lord of hosts is his name;) and thy redeemer the Holy one of Israel: the God of the whole earth shall he be called. Zech.</hi> 14.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And the Lord shall be King over all the earth: in that day shall there be one Lord, and his Name one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all these Premisses I argue thus. No man doubts but the Soul is the original source and first cause of all humane Actions; wherefore the Soul deserves more Punishment then the Body for any sin committed. When <hi>Adam</hi> sinned, both his Soul and Body were obnoxious to Divine Wrath; for the Lord tells <hi>Adam</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Command, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day that thou eatest thereof, thou shalt surely die.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:204172:31"/>
            <p>If it be true what the <hi>Jews</hi> affirm, that this Sentence reacheth onely the death of the Body, since beside the death of the Body, other Curses also are denounced against him, how is it possible it should suit with the great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord, whom they style <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>mercifull in judgment? i. e.</hi> in Justice he remembers Mercy, and alwaies punishes less then the desert. They so much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll God's Mercies, that they curiously note, that whereas in the history of the Deluge it is said, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.11. <hi>The windows of heaven were opened,</hi> and concerning the raining down of <hi>Manna, Psal.</hi> 78.23. <hi>He opened the doors of Heaven;</hi> they observe, I say, that when he rain'd down Judgments, onely the Windows of Heaven were opened, but when he pours down his Blessings, he himself opens the very Doors. And yet farther they observe, that when God manifested his Thirteen Attributes unto <hi>Moses, Exod.</hi> 34.6,7. there are eleven of Mercy, and two onely of Justice. And this being Truth, how can the <hi>Jews</hi> affirm that the sentence of Death, pronounced against <hi>Adam,</hi> extended onely to the death of his Body? Had not <hi>Adam</hi> great reason then to complain for being punished so rigorously, when, over and above the death of his Body, such a showr of Curses are poured out upon him which were not expressed in the Sentence? Might he not well say, O Lord, where are thy <hi>tender mercies?</hi> Is there no <hi>mercy with thee, that thou maist be feared? Shall not the Judge of all the earth doe right?</hi> Why did you not at first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what upon my Transgression you intended to inflict? Where there is no Law, there is no Transgression; and shall a Punishment for a Transgression be executed, which upon the Transgression was not denounced?</p>
            <p>Whence it may appear, that that first Sentence of Death was intended for the Soul, and afterwards God punishes the Body with those Miseries there mentioned, the Body being assistent to the Soul in that action. So that <hi>Adam</hi> by this Sin forfeits three Preeminences which otherwaies he should have enjoy'd: as 1. that he should
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204172:31"/> be exempt from Death; 2. that he should have enjoy'd all Happiness and uninterrupted Felicity in his Mind, of which now, since he must die, he is incapable; 3. that without trouble he should have received all the Comforts of this World convenient for his Body, whereas now the Earth is curs'd for his sake, and in the sweat of his brows he must eat his bread. And on the other side he brings down three Miseries: 1. Death upon himself and his poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; 2. the unexpressible Torments the Sinner suffers in Hell; 3. the Vexations and Miseries Man endures in this World. By this we may know the Loving-kindness of the Lord, and his great Mercy towards all his Creatures, when instantly Divine Love decrees three means to make up these Losses, and to restore Man to his pristine Felicity.</p>
            <p>In the first place, he chuses <hi>Israel</hi> out of all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth for his peculiar People, gives them his Law by the hand of <hi>Moses:</hi> and if we well consider what Reward is promised to the Observers of it, we shall soon discover to what end it was, <hi>viz.</hi> to retrive what <hi>Adam</hi> lost in this World. To <hi>Adam</hi> it was said, <hi>Cursed is the ground for thy sake: Moses</hi> says, <hi>A Land upon which the eys of the Lord thy God are continually, from the beginning of the year unto the end thereof.</hi> To <hi>Adam</hi> it was said, <hi>In sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life: Moses</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises <hi>Plenty, Rest</hi> and <hi>Pleasure. Adam</hi> was subject to the accidents of Fortune, <hi>the Earth brings him Thorns and Thistles,</hi> in stead of Corn: <hi>Moses</hi> promises a peculiar Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence descending to the very Beasts, <hi>I will give grass in thy field even to thy beasts.</hi> To <hi>Eve</hi> it was said, <hi>In sorrow shalt thou bring forth children:</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> saith, <hi>Blessed shalt thou be in the fruit of thy womb.</hi> And so all along.</p>
            <p>But among all these Blessings the Soul is not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And whereas the <hi>Jews</hi> confess the Infelicity and Misery of the Soul by Sin, I would fain know whence the Redemption of it comes: and if for the restauration of a few momentany Pleasures in this transitory life, lost by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204172:32"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi>'s breaking one Command, it was needfull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve 613, for so many are contained in the Law; how many thousands would be necessary for the re-injoyment of those infinite Delights the Soul lost by the same Sin? And if those 613 could not be kept, who will venture to say, he can truly observe so many as might expiate the Soul, if it might be expiated that way?</p>
            <p>And now that it appears clearly that the Reward of keeping the <hi>Mosaical</hi> Law was Temporal Blessings, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite there should be something else for the purgation of the Soul, and restoring it to its former state of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. And since the Lord was pleased to discover to the <hi>Jews</hi> the Secrets of his Will in the Sacred Scriptures, let us search those Scriptures for to find out what may make an Atonement for our Souls.</p>
            <p>We find the Lord gave two eminent Promises to mankind, as pledges of his great Love; which are, of the <hi>Messias,</hi> and the Resurrection. It is sufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that by the Resurrection we recover the other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence <hi>Adam</hi> lost, which is, Life without Death. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> his Law restored the Felicities of this World. What then is left for the <hi>Messias,</hi> but the Redemption of the Soul? And if it be true what the <hi>Jews</hi> say, that the <hi>Messias</hi> comes onely to restore the Kingdom to <hi>Israel,</hi> &amp;c. I wish they would tell me what the Lord hath decreed for the Soul's Happiness, and what means and what time for the full accomplishment of it. All the ancient Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins confess that <hi>Moses</hi> had notice of the <hi>Messias,</hi> and that when he said <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Send now by the hand of him whom thou wilt send,</hi> he intended the <hi>Messias,</hi> who should he come onely to procure the Prosperities of this World, what need had <hi>Moses</hi> to pray for his coming, when at that very time God was sending him to give the Law by the which they are obtained? And if it be true what the <hi>Jews</hi> all acknowledge in their Prayers, that the breath of the Law is the onely cause of losing these Felicities, let them then again keep the Law better then their Fathers
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:204172:32"/> did, and surely, as they believe, they shall enjoy them; and then what need of a <hi>Messias?</hi> Therefore he must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily come for something of greater importance then <hi>Moses</hi> did.</p>
            <p>The Resurrection consummates all the Felicities good men can inherit, which cannot be enjoy'd till the Soul be first cleansed from all its pollutions. We all grant that Man's Perfection was the Creatour's intendment. Sin came into the World, and by Sin Death; and it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for the Soul contaminated with Sin to return to its Centre God: So that we are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that for this Soul to return again, and inform the Body to that end for which it was created, it must first be purified. And since we have proved that the Design and end of the <hi>Messias</hi> his coming is to cleanse us from all Unrighteousness, it remains now to consider the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his coming, whether it be suitable to the Work he hath to doe.</p>
            <p>The ancient Rabbins in the <hi>Midras</hi> say, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is like to the Kingdom of the Earth;</hi> that is to say, by the things of this World we may judge of the things above. Following this method, we may measure the matters of the Soul by the Rules given for the governing of the Body.</p>
            <p>God commands, <hi>Levit.</hi> 4.2. <hi>If</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Nephesh a Soul shall sin through ignorance,</hi> he shall bring such or such an Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. This word <hi>Nephesh</hi> in Scripture-language doth not signifie the Intellectual Soul, which is exprest by <hi>Neshamah Breath;</hi> and the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Ruah</hi> denotes the Sensitive Soul, common to Beasts with Men: as appears <hi>Isai.</hi> 42.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Thus saith God the Lord, he that created the Heavens, and stretched them out; he that spread forth the earth, and that which cometh out of it; he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204172:33"/> walk therein. Neshamah Breath</hi> is to the People, <hi>Ruah Spirit</hi> is to all living creatures; but <hi>Nephesh</hi> denotes the Vegetative Soul, which comprehends also Plants. This being more terrene and inferiour to the rest, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions many errours and mistakes, producing effects contrary oftentimes to the Intellectual Soul, which is all Understanding. Therefore in this place <hi>Levit.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Nephesh</hi> is onely mentioned: and, consequently, we shall find that Sacrifices onely expiated Sins of Ignorance, such as were committed by errour and mistake; but Sins of Wilfulness were not done away by Sacrifices. And though we find some Sins intentionally committed, where Sacrifices were required, as <hi>Levit.</hi> Chap. 6. yet it must be considered that 1. we shall find these Sins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the instigation of the Sensitive Soul: and 2. that these Sacrifices were required onely when the Sin was committed privately, without any witness, the Offender of himself must confess his Sin, Confession be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an evidence of true Repentance; for should he be convicted by Law, he must restore double at the least, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. In this case onely a fifth part, besides the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, and his Trespass-offering. But Sins committed out of pure Malice and an evil intention, where the Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Soul is principally concerned, for such Sins there remains no Sacrifice, neither is any Atonement declared for them throughout the whole Law.</p>
            <p>Now if it is necessary that Sacrifices should be offered for the purification of the Body, we may well judge that the Soul needeth Sacrifices for its purgation. The Body, being brute and earthly, brings of the same quality for its satisfaction; the intellectual Soul for its Atonement must likewise have a Sacrifice someways proportionable to it self. The Angels cannot satisfie, since they were created Guardians for Mankind, and in that Ministeriall office inferiour to the Soul. The <hi>Jews</hi> call them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Angels of service.</hi> And the Soul cannot make an Atonement for it self. So there remains onely God who
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204172:33"/> is able to satisfie. And if the coming of the <hi>Messias</hi> is onely for this end, to make Atonement for the Sins of the Soul, then the <hi>Messias</hi> must be God, as well as Man: and if so, how could this be without that great Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Incarnation? And if this be an infallible truth, we must offer violence to our own Reason, if we do not fully consent to the truth of the Holy Gospel, wherein this Doctrine is clearly and plainly revealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moses</hi> speaks nothing of the Soul: and if other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets darkly hint at it, it is because the coming of the <hi>Messias,</hi> who was designed for the Propitiation of Sin and for the Soul's Redemption, was more fully revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to them. The ancient <hi>Jews</hi> before the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Christ,</hi> though they disputed excellently of all other matters, were very sparing in discoursing of the Soul's Happiness. <hi>Christ</hi> comes, and <hi>brings life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light,</hi> and most fully declares the Soul's eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Felicity after Death: and since that time all the most famous Authours amongst the <hi>Jews</hi> have written large Volumes of it: A sufficient testimony that <hi>Christ</hi> first more clearly revealed and propagated this Truth.</p>
            <p>God created the World in seven days: yet the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness of Men in a few Ages persuaded them to believe that the World was eternall, without beginning; till at length <hi>Moses</hi> came, and by the revelation of God disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Creation of it to his people: which truth by degrees came to be publick and received in most parts of the World. The first Publishers of the Mysteries of the Soul were the Disciples of <hi>Christ,</hi> who learnt it from their Master, who was Lord of the Soul. But the truth is, <hi>Moses,</hi> who came to augment the Felicities of this World, taught the beginning of it, that his People might believe the Authour thereof could govern and dispose of it at his pleasure. <hi>Christ,</hi> who came to redeem the Soul, preach'd the Felicities she should enjoy through the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204172:34"/> shedding of his most precious Bloud.</p>
            <p>When we treated above of the <hi>Jews</hi> mysticall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Temple, we purposely omitted to say any thing of the Altar of Incense over-laid with pure Gold, which was situate in the Holy of Holies, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Veil, before the Mercy-seat, reserving it for this place. This <hi>golden Altar</hi> differed from the <hi>Altar of Burnt-offering</hi> by many degrees of Sanctity. That of the Burnt-offering was placed in the Outer Court, which represents this Earthly Globe; this Golden Altar in the Holy of Holies, representing the Angelicall World: A difference worthy of great consideration, the better to understand the signification of it. Let us see what the use of it was. It is frequently called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the Altar of Incense</hi> or <hi>Perfume,</hi> because thereon <hi>Aaron</hi> burnt sweet Incense every morning, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.7. No manner of Sacrifice was there to be offered, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.9. onely a part of the bloud of some particular Sacrifices, as of the Sin-offerings of the High-Priest and of all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, on <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Day of <hi>Atonement</hi> was sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the Horns thereof, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.18. This Day represented a general Pardon which the Lord prepared to grant, not onely to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but also to the rest of the Nations. The Feast of Tabernacles signified that universal Peace and Happiness the whole World should enjoy. This Festival was to be celebrated on the 15. day of the seventh month; the day of Atonement was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede it 5 days, it being to be solemnized the 10. day of the same month; for Expiation and Pardon of Sin must be before the enjoyment of Felicity can be obtained. So it appears that this great Day of Atonement did sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> who was to be made the Propitiation for the sins of the whole World: therefore it was called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the day of Atonements,</hi> in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to shew that there were more Atonements and Pardons to come then was there declared to the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:204172:34"/> This was the day whereon they were commanded to afflict their Souls, as if it were to signifie the dolorous Agony and Passion of <hi>Jesus;</hi> Pardon being not to be obtained but by much Sorrow and inward Grief. So that the onely meaning of this Day was, to signifie that great Atonement which <hi>Christ</hi> should make.</p>
            <p>This being premised, we may safely affirm that this Golden Altar was a real Representation of <hi>Christ.</hi> It was of Gold, to shew the Pureness of his Body. And the Bloud of this general Sacrifice for the Sins of the Priest and the whole Congregation, on this day to be sprinkled upon this Altar, plainly represents the Bloud of <hi>Christ</hi> to be shed for the general Pardon of the Sins of the World, and that it was impossible to obtain Pardon without shedding of bloud. And this propitiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was to be offered but once a year, to shew that <hi>Christ</hi> was to offer up himself once for all.</p>
            <p>The constant Service of this Altar was, that <hi>sweet In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense should be burnt thereon every morning and every evening, a perpetuall Incense before the Lord, Exod.</hi> 30.7,8. The <hi>Jews</hi> themselves acknowledge that this Perfume sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Prayers of the Righteous, which reach unto the highest Heavens. Wherefore <hi>David</hi> saies, <hi>Psal.</hi> 141.2. <hi>Let my Prayer be set before thee as incense.</hi> Therefore among the ten Wonders which the <hi>Jews</hi> say were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in the Temple, this is one, that the Smoak of this Perfume went directly upwards without the least de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, though the wind blew never so violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Whereupon they say, the Prayers of the just are alwaies effectual, and never are offered up in vain, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all Impediments. So that this Altar of Perfume plainly represents <hi>Christ</hi>'s Mediation and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercession: he makes our Prayers offered up upon this Altar, that is, in his Name, to be accepted before the Lord. And as there was to be a perpetuall Incense be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord upon this Golden Altar which was placed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204172:35"/> in the Holy of Holies, on one side of it, before the Mercy-seat, which denotes the Throne of God; so <hi>Christ</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually sitteth at the right hand of God making Intercessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us.</p>
            <p>The Temple, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> was the place wherein the Lord manifested himself to his people, and wherein as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted that Divinity which had a particular care over them. This was builded of Wood and Stones: and if so, how much more convenient is the Church of God, his chosen People, for his Divine Spirit to assist in the midst of them? And if the Ark covered with Gold was the appointed place for the Lord to appear unto <hi>Moses, Exod.</hi> 25.22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And there I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the Mercy-seat, from between the two cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims which are upon the Ark of the Testimony, of all things which I will give thee in commandment unto the children of Israel:</hi> how much more pure was the Body of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> by the means of which we now enjoy that Preeminence in a far higher measure then they ever did?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moses,</hi> coming onely to restore the Felicities of this World, to obtain them temporal and terrestriall means were sufficient: but to the enjoyment of the Happiness of Souls surely we need means of a far higher nature, such as is <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> by the merits of whose precious Bloud we our selves are now the Temple of the Lord. This is the true sense of the Text, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Trust ye not in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words, saying, The temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord are these.</hi> Which in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> sense is, They are the Temple of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Navel of the Earth,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:204172:35"/> in respect of its being placed between <hi>Asia, Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> call the Temple <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Heart of the World:</hi> and as the Heart in a man's Body is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined somewhat towards the left side; so the Temple on the top of the Mountain was something towards the South side. So that I now presume the meaning of the Prophet to be, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And I will give them one heart, and I will put a new spirit within you; and I will take the stony heart out of their flesh, and will give them an heart of flesh,</hi> (Note, that this Prophecy was told <hi>Ezekiel</hi> at that very time when the Glory of the Lord was departing from <hi>Jerusalem:</hi> signifying by this, that his next coming should be in the Flesh) as if he should say, The Temple, which is the Heart of the World, whose Influence is communicated to all the parts of the Body, which now is of Stone, after the coming of the <hi>Messias</hi> shall be of Flesh: intending here the Mystery of the Incarnation, by which means our Souls are saved. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this, when the <hi>Jews</hi> asked Signs of <hi>Christ,</hi> he answers them, <hi>John</hi> 2.19. <hi>Jesus answered and said unto them, Destroy this Temple, and in three daies I will raise it up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> are very proud of one Argument, which they esteem unanswerable, touching the Eternity of the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> arguing thus: The Will of God is the same with God: He being eternall, his Will doubtless must be eternall. The Law is the explanation of the Will of God. Therefore the Law must be eternall. This they imagine so strong an Argument, that the most wise amongst them believe it enough to convince any <hi>Christian</hi> who holds the Law to be abolished after the coming of the <hi>Messias.</hi> Nor does it satisfie this Doubt to say that the Ten Commandments of the Decalogue are to be kept for ever. For to this they will readily answer,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204172:36"/> That all the Commandments of the Law were equally commanded by the same God; and wherefore should we then make a Distinction? and though these Ten were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly spoken by the Lord himself, and the rest by <hi>Moses</hi> yet the Fountain from whence all the Offspring is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved is the eternall God himself: and why then should we make a Difference?</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Ten Commandments themselves, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as 'tis generally received amongst the <hi>Jews,</hi> were not spoken by the mouth of the Lord, but the Two first onely, as they say. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>I am the Lord thy God, and, You shall have no other Gods, were spoken by the mouth of the Lord.</hi> But the Eight remaining <hi>Moses</hi> delivered. And this they prove thus: for presently after the Ten Commandments it is said, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And they said unto Moses, Speak thou with us, and we will hear: but let not God speak with us, lest we die.</hi> Which they do affirm to succeed immediately after the Second Commandment.</p>
            <p>So that as to the solving of this Doubt touching the Eternity of the Law, I do presume to doe it by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding first another Question to the <hi>Jews:</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer of which will be the same wherewith we will resolve the Question they propound to us.</p>
            <p>Both the ancient and modern <hi>Jews</hi> generally intitle this World <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a World of Action</hi> or <hi>Work,</hi> and the World to come <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a World of Reward:</hi> and according to this they say, in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Pirke Abot,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>An Hour of Pleasure and recreation in the World to come is much better then all the Lives of this World: but an Hour of Repentance and Good works in this World is far better
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204172:36"/> then all the Life of the World to come.</hi> Their meaning is to express the Excellency of the World to come in this their Sentence; but withall to teach men, that it is a far higher Excellency for to know how to gain Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then to enjoy them. Howsoever by this it appears their Opinion was, as we have said, that the Works in this World bring men to enjoy the other.</p>
            <p>It is held for an undoubted Truth and generally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved among all the <hi>Jews,</hi> that the Resurrection is the time wherein the Lord shall recompence every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Works, the Wicked being severely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and the Just enjoying in that World ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Felicities, delighting themselves in the Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Admiration of those Divine Mysteries which then will be made plain to them. A World, they say, where they shall receive the Reward of the Observation of the Law. Whence it appears their Opinion is, That the Law is the Work whereby they hope to gain the World to come.</p>
            <p>Now it is a certain Truth, That the Work and the Reward of it are two distinct things, and the time of the one is not the time of the other: for Reward must come after the Work is finished: otherwise it will be no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Felicity, if intermixt with Labour. If so, then the Law being the Work, it must necessarily cease after the Resurrection, when the <hi>Jews</hi> say the Just shall live many thousand years upon Earth. Now I would ask them where is the Eternity of the Law, since, according to their own Principles, it must needs thenceforth cease, and be no more kept.</p>
            <p>To this they answer, That the Ceasing of the Law then doth not at all alter the Eternity of the Will of God; for when God gave it, he gave it for this very purpose, that is, to gain by it the Enjoyment of the World of life: so that when we come to receive the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of our Works, then the Works cease of themselves;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204172:37"/> and then the Will of God is perfectly accomplished, since he gave it for this very end.</p>
            <p>Now if this Answer be rational, as indeed it is, who can then deny the Ceremonial Law, being a Type and Figure of <hi>Christ,</hi> should cease with his Coming, and so the Will of God to be absolutely come to pass, who hath prepared from everlasting his onely Son for the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mankind, signified in those Ceremonies, which after his Coming naturally ceased? So that those Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are not onely now unnecessary, but the Observation of them will be accounted a sinfull action: for whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever signifies another thing that is to come, it is a sin to observe it after the thing signified is come to pass, for that is an absolute deniall that the thing is already come; and the keeping of it still does proclaim, that the Lord hath not performed his Promise, whenas it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly compleated.</p>
            <p>Let us now search the Scriptures, and we shall find how that God's Laws have been altered according to times and seasons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lev.</hi> 17.3,4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>What man soever there be of the house of Israel that killeth an ox, or lamb, or goat in the camp, or that killeth it out of the camp, And bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to offer an offering unto the Lord before the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Lord; bloud shall be imputed unto that man, he hath shed bloud; and that man shall be cut off from among his people:</hi> Here the <hi>Israelites</hi> are forbidden to eat any Flesh of those three kinds, except it was killed in the Tabernacle, part thereof being first offered to the Lord: But as soon as they came into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Flesh was permitted them to kill where they pleased.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204172:37"/>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.20,21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>When the Lord thy God shall enlarge thy border, as he hath promised thee, and thou shalt say, I will eat flesh, (because thy soul longeth to eat flesh) thou mayest eat flesh whatsoever thy soul lusteth after. If the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen to put his name there be too far from thee; then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy flock, which the Lord hath given thee, as I have commanded thee, and thou shalt eat in thy gates whatsoever thy soul lusteth after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the space of four hundred and fourscore years, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple was built, it was lawfull for the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> to offer Sacrifice any-where; But after the Temple was reared, they were absolutely forbidden to offer any Sacrifice but there. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.13,14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Take heed to thy self that thou offer not thy burnt-offerings in every place that thou seest. But in the place which the Lord shall chuse in one of thy tribes, there thou shalt offer thy burnt-offerings, and there thou shalt doe all that I command thee.</hi> But the truth is, that Sacrifices signifying onely that glorious Offering <hi>Christ</hi> was to make for us; as soon therefore as the Temple was built, which was the true representation of the Body of <hi>Christ,</hi> the Lord would no longer permit Sacrifices to be offered in any other place, to shew that we are to look for <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> signified by the Temple, as above said, and account of him as the onely Offering to expiate Sin.</p>
            <p>I would fain know what the <hi>Jews</hi> will own to be the means whereby they hope to enjoy that miraculous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204172:38"/> of the Resurrection. For by means of the Law, as they imagine, it cannot be expected; for the Law promises nothing but Temporal Blessings, and the Work whereby onely Temporal Blessings are obtained surely cannot be enough to obtain Heavenly ones. So that there needs more then Bodily Actions to deserve eternall Felicities. Wherefore we must needs conclude, that there must be Faith, which is the pure and real action of the Intellectual and eternal Soul.</p>
            <p>Now to satisfie the <hi>Jews</hi> to the full, we must needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from before their eyes a great Stumbling-block, whereat many thousands of this Nation which profess themselves Christians have also stumbled, that is, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the alteration of the Sabbath, which was truly and really intended in the Law to be kept on the Seventh and last Day of the Week, whereas the Christians generally do observe the First day for a Day of Rest. What may be the reason, say the <hi>Jews,</hi> of this great Alteration and Change; the Observation of the Sabbath being one of the chief of the Ten Commandments, which the Christians do confess are not abolished? For the Resolution of this Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will be necessary to discourse distinctly of three principal Points.
<list>
                  <item>1. To whom the Sabbath was given, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether this Precept was given generally to all the World, or onely to the Children of <hi>Israel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. For what cause and in respect of what it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</item>
                  <item>3. To what effect and to what end it was to be observ'd.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As to the first, I say, That it is manifest to all those that have the knowledge of the Sacred Scriptures, that the Sabbath was imposed onely upon the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> and the rest of the Nations never had any Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either divine or natural, to keep it. For if the Lord had intended that any other beside the <hi>Jews</hi> should ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it, he would have laid his command upon them
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204172:38"/> as well as upon the <hi>Jews:</hi> but that he did not so is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as follows.</p>
            <p>After God had created the first Man, he granted him for his Food all that the Earth produced, reserving onely the fruit of one particular Tree, as it is expressed in <hi>Genes.</hi> 1.29. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And God said, Behold, I have given you every herb bearing seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed: to you it shall be for meat.</hi> Where it appears that all manner of Flesh is prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him. The reason is this: It being a certain truth, that all things are God's who created them, if <hi>Adam</hi> had then taken leave to himself to eat any thing besides what God granted him, he should then have incurred the Sin of Robbery, which is to make use of what is not his own. And let no man imagine, that because God gave Man full power over all the Beasts of the earth, that therefore it was lawfull for him to kill any living creature, though for his maintenance: for we see that when God thought good to forbid the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> to eat any flesh but what should be kill'd in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, these very words are there expressed, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Bloud shall be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto that man, he hath shed bloud.</hi> Where it appears the killing of Beasts to them was accounted Murther. Therefore as soon as <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the Ark, when it seemed convenient in the eyes of the Lord Man should eat flesh, he then makes it lawfull for him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Every moving thing that liveth shall be meat for you: even as the green herb have I given you all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that neither to <hi>Adam,</hi> nor to <hi>Noah,</hi> to whom new Laws were given, was the Sabbath commanded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his posterity were commanded to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204172:39"/> circumcised, and to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons the Sinew that lies in the hollow of the Thigh was prohibited: and yet for all these new Laws, none of them were commanded to keep the Sabbath. But as soon as the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> they were commanded to keep it. So that neither <hi>Adam, Noah,</hi> nor <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor their Children, were preobliged to the Observation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, untill after the coming forth out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And so, as Circumcision reacheth no farther then to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his posterity; so none were obliged to keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath but the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> onely, to whom it was commanded equally with the rest of the Precepts of the Law.</p>
            <p>This truth is so absolutely and strictly received by all the <hi>Jews,</hi> that it is given for a general Rule, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>One of the Gentiles that will offer to keep the Sabbath is to be put to death.</hi> Their meaning is, One that is not a Proselyte, which obliges himself to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of all the Law. And the reason is, (say they) because the Sabbath is given for a Sign and token be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and themselves; so that no man else is to meddle therewith.</p>
            <p>From what we have said at the first sight arises a great Question, that is, If it be true (as it is generally believed) that the Sabbath was commanded absolutely in reference to the Creation, to the end Man should acknowledge and confess the Lord the Creatour of all things, wherefore then should it be onely commanded to the <hi>Jews,</hi> since all the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> are equally concerned it it? This being the second Point we are to treat of; to it I say as follows.</p>
            <p>That it is a mistake, to imagine that the Sabbath represents nothing else but the Creation, and that it was onely given for that end and purpose: For if so, the Lord would have enjoyned the Observation of it to <hi>Adam,</hi> and consequently all his Posterity should have been obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204172:39"/> to keep it. But since the Lord did not so doe, there is no question but that the Sabbath represents also some other thing which relates not to the Creation: and so it seems; for when the Lord commanded it to the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> (which was when the <hi>Manna</hi> first descended) in the first sixth day they found a double portion; and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Moses</hi> the reason of it, he told them, the next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing day was to be the Sabbath, whereon the <hi>Manna</hi> should not descend: and that was the first time the Lord commanded that day to be kept. Whereas if the true and onely reason of the observing of it had been the Creation, it should there have been declared to them, being its proper place: but we do not find any thing of it expressed there more then these very words, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23. <hi>And he said unto them, This is that which the Lord hath said, To morrow is the rest of the holy Sabbath unto the Lord.</hi> And whereas by these words <hi>(This is that which the Lord hath said,)</hi> it seems that they had notice of it before; the meaning thereof is this: That whereas <hi>Moses</hi> had already taught them how that the Lord had created the World in six days, and rested the seventh, he now saies here, <hi>(This is that which the Lord hath said;)</hi> that is, The Lord hath decreed and set apart this day, as I told you before, for to give it to you this very day. For this is the meaning of the Text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And God blessed the seventh day, and sanctified it;</hi> that is, he did separate it from the rest of the Days of the Week. This word <hi>Kedusha, Sanctity,</hi> is known to all <hi>Hebricians</hi> to signifie nothing else but <hi>Separation:</hi> so that the Lord then separated this Day for some other end. Therefore when the Lord in the Ten Commandments gives the Rule of the Observation of the Sabbath, it is there said, <hi>Remember the Sabbath</hi>-day, to sanctifie it. Note, that here it is not said, <hi>Keep the Sabbath,</hi> but, <hi>Remember</hi> it; and the reason there given is that of the Creation, <hi>For in six days,</hi> &amp;c. But at the end of that Commandment it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204172:40"/> is said, <hi>Therefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath, and sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it;</hi> that is, he did separate and set it apart, but to what End it is not there expressed.</p>
            <p>And before we proceed farther, it will be necessary to enquire the reason why the Sabbath, being intended for the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> was not commanded to <hi>Abraham,</hi> God's Friend and his beloved, as well as Circumcision, (which also is called a <hi>Sign</hi>) but was manifested onely after the coming out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> The reason of it is this: Presently after the Floud, as we said before, the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness of men grew so high, that they not onely lost the true Tradition received from their Fore-fathers how that the Lord was Maker of all things, but they grew also so insolent as to attempt to invent Reasons wherewith to deceive those that were to come after them, indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to prove it impossible for the World ever to have had a Beginning. This cursed doctrine they impudently taught before the very face of <hi>Sem, Noah</hi>'s Son, who the <hi>Jews</hi> say was <hi>Melchizedek.</hi> The Wickedness of that Age caused him to retire with <hi>Heber,</hi> his great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child, and privately teach the Truth of God. And so the <hi>Jews</hi> say, <hi>Sem</hi> was <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Isaac</hi>'s Master, and <hi>Heber Jacob</hi>'s; for <hi>Sem</hi> died about the 15. year of his age.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> with whom all the Sciences and Philosophy of those times remained, were great professors and maintainers of the World's being <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently that the Lord neither had nor could have any Knowledge of any thing in it, much less have power to alter the Course of Nature. This appears clearly, in that when <hi>Moses</hi> spoke to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the name of the Lord, he proudly answers, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Who is the Lord, that I should hearken to his voice? I know not the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Upon which the Lord was pleased to work there such wonderfull Miracles amongst them, as that he shewed himself to be all-sufficient, and that, as absolute Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204172:40"/> he could order and command Nature at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>Now the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> being Eye-witnesses of this great work of the Lord, wherein the Creation was anew by experience manifested and ascertained, (for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this, after their going forth out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he divided the red Sea for their sake, and shewed them so much of his Power, as to convince them that man lives not by Bread alone, but by the word of the Lord, by feeding them with Heavenly Bread) now, I say, that they were absolutely convinced that the Lord was the onely Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, it was now the proper time to tell them that they were to <hi>remember the Sabbath:</hi> as if he had said, Now you have seen with your own eyes that I am the Maker of all things, now you are to remember, I made them all in six days, and the seventh I did sanctifie, separate and set apart. So that their coming forth of <hi>Egypt</hi> was the cause this Commandment was imposed upon them.</p>
            <p>And this is clearly expressed in the Repetition of the Ten Commandments in <hi>Deuter.</hi> 5. <hi>Keep the Sabbath-day to sanctifie it:</hi> but there is nothing mentioned of the Creation. So that the Sabbath was onely a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Beginning of the World; but the Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it for another reason. Look verse 15. of the same Chapter: <hi>Remember thou wert a Slave,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore the Lord thy God commanded thee to observe the Sabbath-day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we conclude the Sabbath was given onely to the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> and no other Nation obliged to it; and given in respect of nothing else but in memory of the Creation, and of their coming forth out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Prayers appointed for this day call the Sabbath <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the work of the Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we have concluded with the first two of our three Points, we will begin with the third and last, which is, To what End the Sabbath was given. And
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204172:41"/> that the Sabbath doth represent something to come, is out of doubt; for otherwise it would not have been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Sign.</hi> For what-ever doth signifie any thing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy past is onely called a <hi>Remembrance,</hi> as you may finde several Commandments of this nature in the Law; and in this respect the Sabbath it self was called a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, as has been before said. But a <hi>Sign</hi> must needs represent something that is yet to come, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently cease when that thing comes to pass. What then is the thing which the Sabbath represents and is a Sign to? The general Opinion of all the ancient and modern <hi>Rabbies</hi> is as followeth:</p>
            <p>It is certainly believed amongst them all without any contradiction, that in the same day <hi>Adam</hi> was created, in the very same day he sinned, and was cast out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise; and that (though late) he heartily repented, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how by his own Folly he had brought not onely upon himself an infinity of Miseries, but also upon all his Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: whose true Contrition the Lord presently accepted, declaring to him, that though he had lost this World by his Folly, his Divine Majesty had already prepared ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, where he might enjoy what he had lost in this. And this, they say, was represented unto him in the Institution of the Sabbath, which succeeded imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin and Banishment; wherein the Lord shewed him a Cessation from all Labour, Pains and Troubles. Farther, the <hi>Jews</hi> say, that <hi>Adam</hi> then full of Joy did sing Hymns to the Lord for his kind Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphrast, expounding the first Verse of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>Song,</hi> wherein he describes ten Songs to be sung in this World to the Lord, applies the first to <hi>Adam</hi> in the following words: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The first Song</hi> Adam <hi>said at the time that his Sin was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204172:41"/> the day of the Sabbath coming became a Shield or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to him. Then he opened his mouth and said, A Psalm or Song for the Sabbath-day.</hi> So that all that Psalm, being the 92. they say <hi>Adam</hi> composed; which indeed well understood is a plain description of the World to come: for there it is shewn how that the Wicked ones shall be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely punished, though they flourish never so much in this World; and the Just eminently rewarded, though they here suffer many Miseries: Properties really and onely belonging to the World of the Resurrection, where the Name of the Lord will be justified even by the very mouths of the most notorious wicked ones, confessing that their Folly corrupted their waies, though their hearts were inraged against the Lord. And thus that <hi>Psalm</hi> ends, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>To shew that the Lord is upright: he is my rock, and there is no unrighteousness in him.</hi> Therefore in the 56. of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> (which they also understand to the same purpose) the first and second Verses run thus; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Thus saith the Lord, Keep ye judgment and doe justice; for my salvation is near to come, and my righteousness to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. Blessed is the man that doth this, and the son of man that layeth hold on it; that keepeth the Sabbath from pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, and keepeth his hands from doing any evil.</hi> Where it appears the keeping of the Sabbath is applied to that Salvation when the Divine Justice will be openly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested: and therefore in this Text the Sabbath is put on one side, and the observation of all the rest of the Law on the other side, included in these words, <hi>That keepeth his hands from doing any evil:</hi> whence the <hi>Jews</hi> infer their ancient Saying, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Sabbath is as weighty and of as much consequence as all the Law besides.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:204172:42"/>
            <p>Here you see they are of opinion that the Sabbath is a Representation of the World to come: therefore the ancient <hi>Rabbies</hi> call it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>a World which is all Sabbath;</hi> and accordingly they say, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>he that doth not work in the Eve of the Sabbath shall not eat in the Sabbath:</hi> their meaning is, If he does not Good works in this World, he is not to enjoy the other.</p>
            <p>They proceed, and ground this their Opinion upon the Text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And on the seventh day God ended his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made.</hi> Here we see a manifest Contradiction, very hard to be salved without their Exposition; as thus: It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the Lord created all things in six daies, and that before the Sabbath began all his Work was ended; and if so, how does then our cited Text say, that God made an end of his work on the seventh day? It is not possible this can be understood though of the very last moment of the sixth day; for the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>on the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day,</hi> according to all Grammaticall Rules, must needs comprehend part of that day. But according to what we have said it is easie to be understood, as thus:</p>
            <p>God's first intention in the creation of Man was to make him perfect, that he might enjoy those Felicities intended for him. <hi>Adam</hi> on the same day he had his being sinned, whereby he made himself uncapable of those great Enjoyments that were prepared for him. So that now we may safely and properly say, that God had not then made an absolute end of his Work, since <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin hindred and stopped that good End that he was created for, that is, to have been perfect: and now when the Lord had totally finished his Work on his side, <hi>Adam</hi> on his made it defective. But the great God, out of his tender love to mankind, immediately prepared a remedy: the meaning
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:204172:42"/> of our Text being now thus; <hi>The Lord finished his work on the seventh day,</hi> that is, His Mercy decreed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, wherein his first intention should be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished, that being the real end and aim God made Man for. And so we may understand the Text, which indeed is not commonly rendred according to the true sense of the <hi>Hebrew, Gen.</hi> 2.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>And God bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the seventh day, and sanctified it; because that in it he had rested from all his work which God created and made:</hi> but in the true <hi>Hebrew</hi> it is, <hi>which God had created for to make.</hi> And now the sense is plain by what we have said: for though God had made all perfect, yet by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin the full accomplishment of it was reserved for God to doe in the World to come.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> are so settled in this persuasion, that the <hi>Cabalists</hi> are of opinion, the Just ones enjoy in this World an addition of Light and Influence in their Souls on the day of the Sabbath, which they call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>an advantageous Soul,</hi> or an addition to their own Souls. Their meaning is this; That whereas the work of the Just upon the Sabbath is, to delight themselves in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration and contemplation of the World to come, that their Souls being elevated with these glorious thoughts do then receive a few Sparks of that Light they are to enjoy in the other World.</p>
            <p>Now after this Foundation is laid, It being most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as it is above clearly proved, that the Coming of the <hi>Messias</hi> could not be for any other end or purpose but to redeem Souls, cleansing, disposing and preparing them, by the shedding of his precious Bloud, so that they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pure and clean from the filthiness of all Sin by means of Faith in <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> and his continuall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercession, they may become thereby capable of obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Felicities of the World to come: it is also most
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:204172:43"/> certain, that all the Precepts which in the Law are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Signs</hi> do signifie and were a Type of the Coming of the <hi>Messias. Circumcision</hi> was called a Sign and a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, signifying, that that which should bind and unite God and his People should be Bloud; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceased when <hi>Christ</hi> shed his. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> also, which was called a Sign, which the <hi>Jews</hi> confess represented the World of Life, is also without doubt a Type of the <hi>Messias,</hi> by whose means the other World is to be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the Sabbath signifying the Rest of our Souls gained by that most noble Sacrifice. And to evidence this Truth, <hi>Christ</hi> not onely suffered and died for us, but on the third day he rose from the dead, to assure us, we shall enjoy the same Privilege by being true Believers. And if the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath did indeed represent the Resurrection, then of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity it must be a Type of the <hi>Messias,</hi> without whom the Resurrection cannot be obtained. And therefore as soon as <hi>Christ</hi> arose from the dead, that which the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath signified was accomplished and come to pass: and according to that Rule which the <hi>Jews</hi> also own for truth, that when the thing comes to pass which was sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by another, then that which was but a Sign must cease; so at <hi>Christ</hi>'s Resurrection, the Sabbath abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and totally ceased of it self, seeing it was but a Sign to that which then effectually was accomplished. Who can then deny the great reason the Founders of the <hi>Christian</hi> Religion had to institute a day of Rest on the First day of the Week, being that very day wherein <hi>Christ</hi> arose, called properly the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> whenas in it we are possessed effectually of that which the formal Sabbath was but a Sign of?</p>
            <p>And whereas to prove Truths out of the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is something difficult, (the Subtilty of men being such, that they will turn and wind any Text at their own pleasure; and though they have very little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for it, yet it doth suffice to satisfie their own Fancies,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204172:43"/> and to withstand the Truth from those that out of a real Zeal are willing to instruct them) therefore to conclude this my Discourse, I will here set down some few Rules which the <hi>Jews</hi> are not onely not ignorant of, but do esteem them infallible.</p>
            <p>It is common through the whole <hi>Talmud,</hi> that when any one Doctour's Opinion is opposed by another, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging on his side a Text of Scripture, then, if he will not accept of it, he is asked thus, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>This Text to what doth such a Rabbie apply it?</hi> and then he is obliged to expound it in another sense, or otherwise confess himself to be convinced. And when it happens that that Exposition wherewithall he is opposed is not the plain literal sense, which is past contradiction, then commonly he saves himself by saying onely <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Law hath seventy faces,</hi> that is to say, he is not bound to believe his Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, since the Law may be expounded several waies. And finally, the <hi>Cabalists</hi> call the Scriptures <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> a <hi>Garden</hi> or <hi>Orchard,</hi> a word composed of 4 Letters, which they say signifie the four Senses the <hi>Scripture</hi> is to be understood in: by the first Letter, פ <hi>Pe,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Pessatt,</hi> is meant the Literal; by the second, ר <hi>Resh,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Remez,</hi> the Typical or Significative; by the third, ד <hi>Daleth,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Darass,</hi> the Allegoricall; and by the fourth and last, ס <hi>Samech,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Sod,</hi> the Mysticall Sense: so that all these four Senses every Text of Scripture must bear, each one of them producing and bringing forth their several Branches. This is their Allegoricall sense of the Text of the <hi>Song of Solomon,</hi> Chap. 4. verse 13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Thy Plants are an Orchard of Pomegranates:</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rendred <hi>Plants,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Root <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is <hi>to send forth;</hi> and so they interpret this word in that sense, <hi>The things thou sendest forth,</hi> that is, thy Commandments; which indeed are the true Plants, that bear the pleasant Fruit of our
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204172:44"/> Salvation. This being their own Principle, wherefore will the <hi>Jews</hi> then onely stick to the Literal sense, since they know well that things which are promised to come are alwaies delivered, and are to be understood, in one of the other three senses? And I hope that this will be enough for us to know the Mysteries of the <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> are seldom expressed in the plain Literal sense, but rather and more especially in the Typicall sense, and in a far higher measure in the Mysticall.</p>
            <p>And whereas some passages of the Old Testament are in the New expounded for <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> finding those not very proper according to the Literal sense, and some others to have been fulfilled before <hi>Christ</hi> was born, do think it sufficient to overthrow Christianity with it. But they forget their ancient Rule, generally believed by all the ancient <hi>Rabbies,</hi> to this purpose, That many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, though they are given merely with relation to, and accordingly were fulfilled at such a time, yet nevertheless they may comprehend in them some other thing which is yet to come; as is expressed by the following words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>All that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Fathers signifies something that afterwards will happen to their Sons.</hi> And so they reckon of all the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages that befell <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> both as to Troubles and Deliverances, equallizing and comparing them to those that happened to the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
            <p>As for example; <hi>Abraham</hi> went down to <hi>Egypt,</hi> and there he was troubled for his Wife's sake by King <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh;</hi> but God delivered him, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> gave him a great many Gifts. This they say represents the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of <hi>Egypt,</hi> whence after their Troubles they came forth with much Riches. <hi>Isaac</hi> digged 3 Wells; the two first the Herdsmen of <hi>Gerar</hi> strove for, but the third he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in peace. And because God's Influence in the Scripture is termed <hi>waters,</hi> as in <hi>Isaiah, O ye all that are dry,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204172:44"/> goe to the water,</hi> and in another place, <hi>You shall draw water with joy from the fountain of Salvation;</hi> therefore they say these three Wells of water <hi>Isaac</hi> digged represented the three Temples, two that are destroyed, and the third that they hope for to remain in peace. <hi>Jacob,</hi> to avoid his Brother's Rage, sends him a Present. That they say signifies, that when they be in Captivity they must appease their Enemies with Gifts.</p>
            <p>And if so, why should the <hi>Jews</hi> then wonder that there may be several passages in Scripture that, though they did formerly happen to be fulfilled, yet <hi>Christ</hi> may be signified in them?</p>
            <p>To conclude: I do not think it amiss to embrace that ancient Saying of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>The Sabbath is as weighty, and of as much consequence, as all the rest of the Law besides.</hi> For it being true that the Law is divided into two parts, the Moral and Ceremonial, the Sabbath, being the chief of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, is a Sign of Signs, a Type of Types, and the onely Ceremony of all Ceremonies; all the rest being comprehended in it: for it represents both the Rest of the Soul after death, and that of Soul and Body at the Resurrection, and consequently our blessed Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> by whose means all these Felicities are obtained.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>